<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

	<title>Technically Exists</title>
	<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/archive/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/archive"/>
	<updated>2021-03-08T02:42:39+00:00</updated>
	<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/archive</id>
	<author>
		<name>BTernaryTau</name>
	</author>

	
		<entry>
			<title>On dealbreaker voting criteria</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2021/03/07/on-dealbreaker-voting-criteria"/>
			<updated>2021-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2021/03/07/on-dealbreaker-voting-criteria</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/2021/01/24/social-choice-theory-paradigms&quot;&gt;my previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I argued that probabilistic analysis was superior to pass/fail analysis as an approach to social choice theory. As a quick recap, pass/fail analysis tries to identify desirable criteria, then figure out which methods pass them and which methods don’t. Probabilistic analysis instead tries to identify how often failures of these criteria occur and how severe those failures are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One consequence of pass/fail analysis is that it’s tempting to adopt what I would call a “dealbreaker criterion”, a voting criterion which a voting method must pass for you to even consider recommending it. If a voting method fails that criterion, it doesn’t matter if it is otherwise great; that failure is a dealbreaker. I’m not sure how many people actually do this, but I do know that it’s common to pick a criterion to emphasize as being crucial, which at the very least comes close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example of this would be the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparison_of_electoral_systems#Strategy_criteria&quot;&gt;favorite betrayal criterion&lt;/a&gt;, which is passed if voters are never incentivized to give less than maximum support to their favorite candidate. One of the leading voting reform organizations, the Center for Election Science, places a lot of emphasis on this criterion. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://electionscience.org/approval-voting-faqs/&quot;&gt;their FAQ page&lt;/a&gt;, the first bullet point after the question “How is approval voting better than our current system?” is “Voters can always vote for their favorite candidate, whether they have a good or bad chance of winning”. The two single-winner methods they support, approval voting and score voting, both pass the favorite betrayal criterion. At the very minimum this is quite close to being a dealbreaker criterion for them, and it’s highly likely that some of their members do hold it as a dealbreaker criterion even if the organization doesn’t quite do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a dealbreaker criterion means that you care about pass/fail analysis for that criterion, since you’re not interested in supporting any method that fails it. It doesn’t matter if a voting method fails favorite betrayal only 1% of the time; you want to feel 100% safe about voting for your favorite, not 99%! While this seems like a reasonable position to take, it leads to some surprising conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, while single-winner approval voting passes the favorite betrayal criterion, &lt;a href=&quot;https://electionscience.org/voting-methods/getting-proportional-with-approval-voting/&quot;&gt;the proportional version&lt;/a&gt; that the Center for Election Science supports does not. In fact, essentially no proportional method passes this criterion, including every method currently in use, so adopting it as a dealbreaker pretty much means opposing proportional representation. This is not at all obvious, and I expect that most proponents of the favorite betrayal criterion haven’t really wrangled with this implication, especially if they consider favorite betrayal to be a dealbreaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sort of thing happens often enough that it’s turned me off of having any dealbreaker criteria. As a couple more examples, the Center for Range Voting strongly supports the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Participation_criterion&quot;&gt;participation criterion&lt;/a&gt;, but recommends reweighted range voting even though it fails participation. Likewise, the Equal Vote Coalition strongly supports the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bternarytau.github.io/miscellaneous/voting-theory/cancellation-criterion&quot;&gt;cancellation criterion&lt;/a&gt;, but recommends allocated score voting even though it fails this criterion. It’s debatable whether the level of support for these criteria is high enough for them to truly be dealbreakers, but even if we assume they aren’t, it’s clear that adopting them as dealbreakers would have surprising consequences for those organizations’ recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another reason I dislike pass/fail analysis. The way it encourages people to adopt dealbreaker criteria can lead them to quickly reject voting methods without thinking through whether the failure of that criterion is really bad enough to dismiss the method. Under probabilistic analysis, this approach is much less natural than one that weights failures of criteria based on how frequent and severe they are, which captures a lot more information than simply having a dealbreaker criterion.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Social choice theory paradigms</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2021/01/24/social-choice-theory-paradigms"/>
			<updated>2021-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2021/01/24/social-choice-theory-paradigms</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Within social choice theory, there are two major approaches to evaluating voting methods: pass/fail analysis and probabilistic analysis. Pass/fail analysis primarily consists of defining mathematical criteria that seem desirable to have, then proving which methods pass them and which methods fail them. It also has other aspects like proving that certain sets of criteria cannot all be satisfied by the same voting method; this is where the famous &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arrow%27s_impossibility_theorem&quot;&gt;Arrow’s impossibility theorem&lt;/a&gt; comes from. On the other hand, probabilistic analysis does away with this and instead assesses voting method performance using simulations and, where possible, data from real-world elections. This approach has its downsides, but overall I think it is by far the superior evaluation method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a simple example of the limitations of pass/fail analysis, I’d like to consider &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reversal_symmetry&quot;&gt;reversal symmetry&lt;/a&gt;. Reversal symmetry is passed if reversing the preferences of every voter will always result in a different winner when there are at least two candidates running. The idea behind this criterion is that voting methods should not consider the best candidate to also be the worst candidate. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plurality_voting&quot;&gt;Single-choice plurality&lt;/a&gt; fails reversal symmetry, since it is possible for one candidate to have both a plurality of first-choice support and a plurality of last-choice “support”, which becomes first-choice support if preferences are inverted. On the other hand, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Approval_voting&quot;&gt;approval voting&lt;/a&gt; passes reversal symmetry, since the candidate with the most approvals cannot also be the candidate with the least approvals.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about a method that almost never violates reversal symmetry, but can do so in a very specific type of scenario? Enter &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/STAR_voting&quot;&gt;STAR voting&lt;/a&gt;. For elections with fewer than 3 candidates, STAR voting will never fail reversal symmetry, and the same holds for elections with more than 3 candidates. However, there is one type of 3 candidate election that causes STAR to fail reversal symmetry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;overflow-x:auto;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;table&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Number of Voters&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Candidate A&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Candidate B&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Candidate C&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, Candidate A receives 10 points, Candidate B receives 9 points, and Candidate C receives 6 points, so A and B are the finalists. A is favored over B on 2 ballots while B is favored over A on 3 ballots, so B is the winner under STAR. What happens if we then invert these voters’ preferences?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;overflow-x:auto;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;table&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Number of Voters&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Candidate A&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Candidate B&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Candidate C&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Candidate A receives 15 points, Candidate B receives 16 points, and Candidate C receives 19 points, so B and C are the finalists. B is favored over C on 3 ballots while C is favored over B on 2 ballots, so B is again the winner under STAR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This failure only happens in elections with 3 candidates A, B, and C, where scorewise A&amp;gt;B&amp;gt;C, but pairwise C&amp;gt;B&amp;gt;A. In any other election, STAR will pass reversal symmetry. But in pass/fail analysis, STAR is just considered to fail the criterion, with no consideration as to how often this failure might occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the first big problem with pass/fail analysis; it doesn’t consider how frequently a method fails a given criterion. Proving that a method passes a criterion is useful, as that tells us that the method fails it 0% of the time. Constructing an example election where a method fails a criterion is much less useful, as we have no idea whether the method fails it 1% of the time or 99% of the time. In contrast, probabilistic analysis is specifically geared toward figuring out criterion failure rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other big problem with pass/fail analysis is that it ignores the severity of failures. This is especially important when it comes to strategic voting. There is a big difference between incentivizing semi-honest voting, where voters may have to rank or rate A equal to B when they really prefer A to B, and incentivizing voters to reverse their preferences, ranking or rating B above A when they prefer A to B. Likewise, there is a big difference between strategic voting leading to a slightly less popular candidate being elected, and strategic voting leading to &lt;a href=&quot;https://electowiki.org/wiki/Dark_horse_plus_3_rivals&quot;&gt;the least popular candidate being elected&lt;/a&gt;. Probabilistic analysis can capture these details in a way that pass/fail analysis cannot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example of this, I’d like to introduce the concept of &lt;a href=&quot;http://electionscience.github.io/vse-sim/VSEbasic/&quot;&gt;Voter Satisfaction Efficiency&lt;/a&gt; (VSE). VSE is a measure of the accuracy of voting methods that is obtained using simulations. The highest possible VSE is 100%, which corresponds to always choosing the best available candidate. A VSE of 0% corresponds to choosing a candidate uniformly at random, and a negative VSE corresponds to performing worse than chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To calculate the Voter Satisfaction Efficiency for a given voting method, you first simulate thousands of elections under that method. You then calculate how well-liked each candidate is by the electorate, and use those values along with the knowledge of which candidate the voting method chose in each election to obtain a final value for that method’s VSE. Importantly, this cannot be done using elections in real life because we have no reliable way of determining how satisfied with each candidate each voter would be. Using simulated voters eliminates this problem, and it also allows us to use a greater number of elections for the calculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to comparing VSE across different voting methods, we can also compare VSE across different voter behaviors. This allows us to capture details and nuances that pass/fail analysis usually misses. One great example of this is present in &lt;a href=&quot;http://electionscience.github.io/vse-sim/VSE/&quot;&gt;Jameson Quinn’s VSE simulations&lt;/a&gt;. In these simulations, Quinn compares a number of voting methods under several different behaviors, including all honest voters and all strategic voters. If we only focus on &lt;a href=&quot;https://electowiki.org/wiki/Borda_count&quot;&gt;Borda count&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://electowiki.org/wiki/Score_voting&quot;&gt;score voting&lt;/a&gt; with a 0-10 ballot, we can see that under honesty, both have a VSE of around 97%, which is really good. However, if we switch to considering their behavior under strategic voting, we find that score now has a VSE of 96%, which is a little lower, but not much. On the other hand, Borda’s VSE drops all the way to -11%! It turns out that rather than being a mere hypothetical, it is actually possible for strategic voting to cause one of the worst possible candidates to be elected so often that the voting method underperforms &lt;em&gt;selecting a candidate completely at random&lt;/em&gt;. This is the sort of detail that the usage of pass/fail analysis risks overlooking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the issue with pass/fail analysis lies in the “fail” part. If a method passes a criterion, then we know both the frequency and severity of failures, which is very useful. It’s when a method fails a criterion that we find ourselves knowing that the method isn’t perfect, but almost nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For simplicity, we ignore all elections in which ties occur, as is common in pass/fail analysis. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>The motivation behind SPSV, part 5</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/10/27/the-motivation-behind-spsv-part-5"/>
			<updated>2020-10-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/10/27/the-motivation-behind-spsv-part-5</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog post has been adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/SimDemocracy/comments/ieogtk/the_motivation_behind_spsv_series/&quot;&gt;a series of posts&lt;/a&gt; written for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/SimDemocracy/&quot;&gt;r/SimDemocracy&lt;/a&gt;. If you haven’t read the previous entries, please start with &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/10/23/the-motivation-behind-spsv-part-1&quot;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last post, we went over how RRV extends SPAV to work with 0-&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; rated ballots. I mentioned that SPSV also extends SPAV to work with such ballots, but that it does so using a different method. In this post, I want to start off by explaining how this method works and why I find it superior to RRV’s approach. After this, we can move on to the full explanation of the motivation behind SPSV and to comparisons with other proportional methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;section-a-the-kotze-pereira-transformation&quot;&gt;Section A: The Kotze-Pereira transformation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extension method that SPSV uses is called the Kotze-Pereira transformation, or KP transform for short. The basic idea behind the KP transform is that it’s possible to use approval ballots as building blocks for creating a score ballot. As an example, let’s use a 0-3 rated ballot that rates candidate A 0, candidate B 1, candidate C 2, and candidate D 3. We can construct this ballot out of 3 approval ballots by having the first ballot approve B, C, and D, the second approve C and D, and the third approve only D. That way, each candidate’s score equals the number of approvals they have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t our only option though. We could also use 1 ballot that approves B and D, and 2 ballots that approve C and D. This is a problem because not only do we want to construct score ballots from approval ballots, we also want to decompose score ballots into approval ballots. Thus, we need a means of choosing a unique set of approval ballots for each score ballot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that there’s a pretty intuitive criterion we can use. Specifically, we can restrict ourselves to only using approval ballots that “stack” on top of each other. By that, I mean there must be some way to order the ballots such that approvals are never added to subsequent ballots, only removed. Intuitively, this means that if each ballot was a row of toy blocks, then you could stack them on top of each other, like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;B&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;C&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;D&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the second set of ballots cannot be stacked on top of each other:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;B&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;C&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;D&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;✅&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the approvals were toy blocks, the approval for B would need to floating in the air. If we try to solve this by moving the B and D ballot to the bottom, we find that the approvals for C would need to be floating. Thus, there is no valid way to stack these ballots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that there is exactly one set of approval ballots that act as stackable building blocks for every possible score ballot. Constructing this set is simple: if a candidate receives &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; points from a score ballot, stack &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; approvals in that candidate’s column. Once you’ve done this for every candidate, the rows will form the desired approval ballots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how the KP transform transforms a 0-&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; score ballot into &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; approval ballots. From here, it’s simple to describe how SPSV works: run the KP transform on every voter’s score ballot, then run SPAV on the resulting approval ballots. That’s it. That’s the entire voting method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;section-b-comparison-with-rrv&quot;&gt;Section B: Comparison with RRV&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s probably not clear whether the above process gives results that differ from those that RRV gives. However, since RRV and SPSV are considered different methods, you can probably guess that the answer is yes. It may not be immediately apparent what the differences are, but after exploring a simple example they should be much clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let’s look at how electing a bunch of candidates that a voter slightly supports affects their ballot weight. We’ll consider an election with candidates A-G, where the voter rates A 5 and all other candidates 1. C will be elected first, then D, then E, and so on. We’ll look at how many points this voter’s ballot contributes toward both A and B as more candidates are elected, under both 0-5 RRV and 0-5 SPSV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Candidate&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Method&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;N/A&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;C&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;D&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;E&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;F&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;G&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;RRV&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.17&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.57&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2.78&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SPSV&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.33&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.25&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.17&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;B&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;RRV&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.83&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.71&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.63&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.56&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;B&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SPSV&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.33&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.25&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.17&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with candidate A. Both methods start with the original score of 5. After C is elected, we can see that RRV has deweighted the ballot more harshly, going down to a 4.17 compared to SPSV’s 4.5. By the time G is elected, RRV has deweighted the ballot all the way to 2.5, while SPSV has only now reached 4.17. If we were to continue electing candidates with a rating of 1, RRV’s rating will approach 0 while SPSV’s rating will approach 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on to candidate B, both voting methods start with a score of 1. The election of C prompts RRV to reduce the score to 0.83, while SPSV brings it all the way down to 0.5. Once G has been elected, RRV finally reaches 0.5, while SPSV is now all the way at 0.17. Continuing to elect candidates rated 1 would lead to both scores approaching 0, but SPSV’s score does so quicker than RRV’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This example shows that SPSV prioritizes preserving the strength of ratings for highly-preferred candidates, and deprioritizes preserving the strength of ratings for weakly-preferred candidates. This effect is strongest when the deweighting results from electing a weakly-preferred candidate. In contrast, RRV deweights all ratings equally, regardless of how preferred the elected candidate was. Personally, I think SPSV interprets my ballot in a more faithful way than RRV does, and I would guess that most people would feel similarly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;section-c-visualizing-representation-accuracy&quot;&gt;Section C: Visualizing representation accuracy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to choosing a good voting method, how faithfully it interpets ballots is not the only important factor to consider. We also want to take into account the accuracy of the voting methods in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to visualize this, I’m first going to have to set up the scenario in which the elections take place. In this scenario there are three factions: the cyan group, the magenta group, and the yellow group. There are three seats available, and each group is running three candidates. Every voter gives the same ratings to candidates if they are from the same group. Those ratings are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Voter Group&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Cyan Candidates&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Magenta Candidates&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Yellow Candidate&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cyan&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3/10&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Magenta&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0/10&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Yellow&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5/10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10/10&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, the only detail we haven’t covered is the distribution of the three groups of voters. I’ve saved this for last because we actually won’t be looking at single distribution of the three groups, but rather all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/0-electorate.png&quot; alt=&quot;Electorate plot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an example of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ternary_plot&quot;&gt;ternary plot&lt;/a&gt;. This particular ternary plot shows the proportion of the electorate that each group makes up. In the top-left corner, the electorate consists of only cyan voters. In the top-right corner, the electorate consists of only magenta voters. And if you couldn’t guess, in the bottom corner the electorate consists of only yellow voters. As you move closer to the center, the mix of voters becomes more even, until you reach the center where each faction makes up exactly 1/3 of the electorate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you’ve seen the voter distribution, we’re going to look at what the winners look like for each of these possible electorates. We’ll start with a method we covered a while back, D’Hondt. Since D’Hondt uses single-mark ballots, each group will simply vote for a candidate from their faction. The distribution of winners looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/1-dhondt.png&quot; alt=&quot;D'Hondt plot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the colors represent how many candidates were elected from each faction. In the top-left, all elected candidates were from the cyan faction, so the area is colored cyan. Below that, we see a greenish-aqua color. This represents the election of two cyan candidates and one yellow candidate. If we then move to the right, we see a gray area that represents the election of one candidate from each group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, D’Hondt behaves pretty nicely when voters can easily be divided into factions. However, because it uses single-mark ballots, it cannot take into account anything other than voters’ first preferences. Thus, even in this favorable scenario it still can’t behave optimally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we’ll take a look at how RRV behaves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2-rrv.png&quot; alt=&quot;RRV plot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple things to notice here. First of all, this plot doesn’t look nearly as nice as the one for D’Hondt. This is pretty much an inevitable result of using information beyond first preferences. However, RRV actually doesn’t do that bad, all things considered. If you’re curious, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.electionscience.org/t/sequential-multiwinner-voting-methods-visualized/773&quot;&gt;check out how other proportional rated methods perform&lt;/a&gt; for yourself; you’ll see that many of them have larger concave areas and appear far more irregular than RRV does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on, the other thing to notice is that the plot is no longer symmetrical. Looking at the corners, the cyan area is larger than the other two, and the yellow area is the smallest. This reflects how the cyan candidates each receive 7 points from every magenta voter, and thus have a lot of second-choice support. Yellow, on the other hand, has very little second-choice support, and this is reflected in its smaller area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last method we will look at is, of course, SPSV. Here is its plot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/3-spsv.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPSV plot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, it looks pretty similar to RRV’s plot, which makes sense given that they are both extensions of SPAV. The main difference is that the center region is larger while the corner regions are all smaller. In fact, SPSV’s regions vary in size less than RRV’s do. The variance between the different corners hasn’t changed much, since SPSV still takes second choices into account. However, RRV had an oddly small center region, indicating that it is biased toward only representing two factions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is easier to observe if we increase the number of seats available. Below are the plots for RRV and SPSV when filling 10 seats instead of 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/4-rrv-ten-seats.png&quot; alt=&quot;RRV 10 seat plot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/5-spsv-ten-seats.png&quot; alt=&quot;SPSV 10 seat plot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might’ve guessed, the top plot is for RRV while the one below is for SPSV. The region outlined in black on each plot is the area in which all 3 factions have at least one candidate elected. In RRV, this area is really small, around 1/4 the size of the whole ternary plot. In SPSV, this area takes up all but the outer edge of the plot. A faction will only be completely excluded by SPSV if it makes up a really small proportion of the population, in which case there simply aren’t enough seats to fairly include them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that everyone reading this feels that they have a better understanding of SPSV, or at least enjoyed themselves along the way. I know that this stuff can seem very complicated, and I’m not always able to explain things well. I encourage you to comment below with any questions you may have, and I’ll do my best to make things clearer. Thank you for reading! ❤️&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>The motivation behind SPSV, part 4</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/10/26/the-motivation-behind-spsv-part-4"/>
			<updated>2020-10-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/10/26/the-motivation-behind-spsv-part-4</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog post has been adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/SimDemocracy/comments/ieogtk/the_motivation_behind_spsv_series/&quot;&gt;a series of posts&lt;/a&gt; written for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/SimDemocracy/&quot;&gt;r/SimDemocracy&lt;/a&gt;. If you haven’t read the previous entries, please start with &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/10/23/the-motivation-behind-spsv-part-1&quot;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last post, we considered how to improve upon the strange behavior that D’Hondt has when dealing with voters that have preferences which don’t match up with party lines. We went over how SPAV modifies the approach that D’Hondt used by reweighting individual ballots instead of a party’s full set of votes, and how this allows it to handle more complex voter groups in a sensible manner. This gave voters more freedom to express their preferences, but they still had to either fully support or not at all support each candidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can SPAV be adapted to use 0-&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; rated ballots instead of approval ballots? As it turns out, this is fairly straightforward to do. Instead of using the formula 1/(1 + &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;), we can use 1/(1 + &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;), where &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt; is the sum of all the scores given to candidates who have already been elected. This method is known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://electowiki.org/wiki/Reweighted_Range_Voting&quot;&gt;Reweighted Range Voting&lt;/a&gt; (RRV), where range voting is used as a synonym for score voting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; is 1, then &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt; will simply be the number of already elected candidates who were given a score of 1, which means it will have the same value as &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;. Thus, RRV behaves exactly the same as SPAV when &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = 1. In fact, this occurs in any instance where it is guaranteed that &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;, which corresponds to voters choosing to use only the minimum and maximum scores, not any intermediate scores. This parallels how score voting behaves like approval voting when voters don’t use intermediate scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we know how RRV can behave similarly to SPAV, let’s consider how it can behave differently. Under SPAV, when a candidate a voter liked was elected, the ballot weight would change to the next number in the sequence 1, 1/2, 1/3, 1/4, etc. However, under RRV the next weight always depends on how much the voter liked the candidate. As an example, let’s consider a single 0-5 ballot in a 7 candidate election under RRV. The ballot has been cast as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Candidate&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Rating&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;B&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;C&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;D&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;E&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;F&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;G&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a table showing how the weight of the ballot changes after the election of each candidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Candidate Elected&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Rating&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;New Ballot Weight&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;None&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;N/A&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1/2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;C&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5/12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;F&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5/12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;E&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5/16&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;B&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5/17&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;D&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5/22&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;G&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5/24&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reveals a rather interesting pattern. If we rewrite 1 as 5/5 and 1/2 as 5/10, then the denominator always increases by the score given to the elected candidate. And looking back at our formula, if we multiply both the numerator and the denominator by &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;, we find that it is equivalent to &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;/(&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;), which in this case is 5/(5 + &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;). Since &lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt; is  the sum of all the scores given to candidates who have already been elected, it will start at 0 and increase by the score given to the elected candidate each round, and thus we have our pattern. While this isn’t the standard way to write this formula, I find that it gives more intuition for how the weights of the ballots change as candidates are elected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is a pretty nice method of extending SPAV to 0-&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; rated ballots, it isn’t the only way of doing so. In the next post, I’ll explain the alternate method that SPSV uses and compare it to this one.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>The motivation behind SPSV, part 3</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/10/25/the-motivation-behind-spsv-part-3"/>
			<updated>2020-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/10/25/the-motivation-behind-spsv-part-3</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog post has been adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/SimDemocracy/comments/ieogtk/the_motivation_behind_spsv_series/&quot;&gt;a series of posts&lt;/a&gt; written for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/SimDemocracy/&quot;&gt;r/SimDemocracy&lt;/a&gt;. If you haven’t read the previous entries, please start with &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/10/23/the-motivation-behind-spsv-part-1&quot;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous post we went over how going from closed party-list to D’Hondt allowed voters to have a say in which candidates are elected from each party while still maintaining proportionality. However, we were still using single-mark ballots like those employed under plurality voting, also known as first-past-the-post. This meant each voter could only support one candidate along with that candidate’s party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This causes two problems, one with allocating seats to parties and one with assigning seats a party won to that party’s candidates. First of all, because voters can only support a single party, similar parties risk splitting the vote with each other. Because seats are assigned proportionally, this isn’t too much of a problem, but when D’Hondt has to decide how to round the level of support for each party to allow an integer number of seats to be assigned, it will tend to favor larger parties at the expense of smaller ones. Tweaking the formula can change what size of parties are favored, but it cannot remove the favoritism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second problem is that within a party, seats are assigned using what is essentially multi-winner plurality voting. This leads to a potentially much more severe vote-splitting problem than what occurs between parties. Thus, factions within a party are incentivized to run the minimum number of candidates that they predict will be able to win seats, which will often just be 1 or 2. If a party is uniform enough to not have factions, then internal vote-splitting will likely be far less of a concern than it is for other parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One possible idea for solving this problem is switching to rated ballots. When D’Hondt was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/SimDemocracy/comments/flnjey/dhondt_method_partylist_proportional/&quot;&gt;proposed in SimDemocracy&lt;/a&gt;, it used 0-5 rated ballots, not single-mark ballots. Perhaps this could solve the problem? For simplicity, instead of 0-5 ballots, I will consider switching to approval ballots instead. Since approval ballots are equivalent to 0-1 rated ballots, any insights gained should transfer over to more expressive ballots as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first proposal for a form of D’Hondt with rated ballots was quite simple: all it did was replace the number of votes a candidate or party earned with the number of points that candidate or party earned. With approval ballots, this would simply be the number of approvals earned. Unfortunately, this turns out to be a very bad idea. Since parties can gain extra approvals by running more candidates, they are incentivized to run as many candidates as they can. In an extreme (albeit unrealistic) case, a party could win every single seat with only 1 voter just by running enough candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible to fix this problem and restore proportionality while still using approval ballots. Instead of taking the number of approvals earned for each party, we can use the number of approvals earned divided by the number of candidates the party ran. So if a party ran 1 candidate, it would get 1 point from every voter approving its candidate, and if another party ran 5 candidates, it would get 1 point from every voter approving all 5 of its candidates. Thus, running more candidates cannot automatically give a party more seats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this new method still has a weird way of interpreting its ballots. For voters who support a single party but choose to vote for only some of its candidates, even though they clearly prefer this party to all others, they won’t give that party their full support. Instead, rated D’Hondt notices that they decided to only vote for some fraction of the party’s candidates, and thus has them give the party that fraction of the maximum possible amount of support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rated D’Hondt behaves even more weirdly when a voter doesn’t vote within party lines. As an example, consider a voter who doesn’t care about ideology much, and instead votes mostly based on which candidates they believe are the most competent. It is very likely that such a voter will approve candidates from many different parties. However, when it comes time to allocate seats, rated D’Hondt will only be able to see party divisions. It cannot allocate seats for competent candidates unless those candidates decide to leave their parties and form a new one, which is unlikely and shouldn’t be necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, what we need is a more general form of proportionality, one that accounts for the fact that rated ballots allow voters to support candidates from multiple parties and choose which of a party’s candidates to support. It actually turns out that multiple such forms of proportionality exist. However, if we want a method that behaves similarly to D’Hondt, we’ll want to look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://electowiki.org/wiki/Sequential_proportional_approval_voting&quot;&gt;sequential proportional approval voting&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of its long name, sequential proportional approval voting is usually just abbreviated as SPAV. SPAV allocates seats one at a time like D’Hondt does, but it gives them directly to candidates rather than giving them to parties and then choosing candidates. The first seat just goes to the candidate with the most approvals. For the next seat, each ballot that approved of the winning candidate is given a weight of 1/2, which means it only gives half of an approval to each candidate it approves; then the candidate with the most weighed approvals wins the second seat. This continues for each available seat, with every ballot having a weight of 1/(1 + &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;), where &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; is the number of candidates approved on that ballot that have won seats so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can demonstrate both SPAV’s proportionality and its similarity to D’Hondt by looking at an example election where all voters vote exactly along party lines. Once again we can reuse our example from the first post. 50 voters will support candidates A1-A10, 30 voters will support candidates B1-B10, and 20 voters will support candidates C1-C10. We’ll assume that ties are broken in alphanumeric order (the order where A1 comes before A2, which comes before B1). The election proceeds as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Round&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;A1-A10&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;B1-B10&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;C1-C10&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Winner&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;50&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;30&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;B1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;25&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;16.67&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;20&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;C1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;16.67&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;15&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;B2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;12.5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A4&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;10&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;A5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.33&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;10&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;B3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.33&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;10&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;C2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the numbers in this table look familiar, it’s because they’re the exact same numbers that appeared in the table for D’Hondt in the last post. And as you would expect, the winners included 5 candidates from party A, 3 from B, and 2 from C. However, SPAV achieved this result without knowing anything about which candidates belonged to which parties. Instead, it used the fact that there was a group of ballots approving A1-A10, another group approving B1-B10, and a third group approving C1-C10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But importantly, this approach extends to cases where the ballots can’t be neatly divided into groups. Since every ballot is reweighted individually, SPAV can handle complex relations between partially overlapping groups that methods like D’Hondt don’t even try to deal with. This makes it a major improvement in terms of the types of preferences that voters can express.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there’s still room to improve upon this. Right now voters must decide between fully supporting a candidate and not supporting a candidate at all. But we know that rated ballots can allow voters to express significantly more nuanced opinions. The next post will take a look at a proportional method that’s similar to SPAV but can handle ballots with more ratings.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>The motivation behind SPSV, part 2</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/10/24/the-motivation-behind-spsv-part-2"/>
			<updated>2020-10-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/10/24/the-motivation-behind-spsv-part-2</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog post has been adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/SimDemocracy/comments/ieogtk/the_motivation_behind_spsv_series/&quot;&gt;a series of posts&lt;/a&gt; written for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/SimDemocracy/&quot;&gt;r/SimDemocracy&lt;/a&gt;. If you haven’t read &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/10/23/the-motivation-behind-spsv-part-1&quot;&gt;the previous entry&lt;/a&gt;, please do so.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen that closed party-list gives more representative outcomes than non-proportional methods like bloc score. However, it also failed to give voters a say in which candidates from a given party would be elected. In the previous post’s example election, this didn’t matter since the voters didn’t have opinions on the individual candidates anyway. But what happens when they do have such opinions, as is the case in real elections?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the parties all share their voters’ preferences, then this isn’t a problem since the party can just choose the candidates the voters want. But if party insiders prefer a different set of candidates, then the voters could feel cheated out of their say in which candidates get elected. Needless to say, this should not happen in a legitimate election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way of fixing this problem is to switch to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/D%27Hondt_method&quot;&gt;D’Hondt method&lt;/a&gt;. This method is named after Belgian mathematician Victor D’Hondt, who came up with it in 1878. However, it was actually first proposed by Thomas Jefferson in 1792, so it is sometimes referred to as Jefferson’s method instead. Instead of casting a vote for a single party, voters cast their vote for a single candidate, as is done under single-choice plurality voting. These votes are then used to determine both how many seats each party gets and which candidates from each party are elected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To allocate seats, every party is assigned the votes received by each of its candidates. The first seat is given to the party with the most votes. For the next seat, the party that won the first seat has its total number of votes halved, and then the party with the most votes remaining wins. This continues for each available seat, with every party having 1/(1 + &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;) of their original vote count, where &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; is the number of seats that party has won so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be thought of as splitting that party’s votes between the seats they’ve already won and the seat they’re trying to win each round. If a party already has 3 seats, then it only has 1/(1 + 3) = 1/4 of its votes remaining since if it won another seat, it would have to split its votes among the 4 seats to justify having all of them. Thus, it can only afford to put 1/4 of its votes toward winning a new seat. This ensures that each seat has approximately the same number of votes allocated to it, as a party that wins 4 seats will have needed about 4 times as many votes to do so as a party that wins 1 seat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once all seats have been allocated, it is simple to assign candidates to them. For each party, assign the first seat that party won to the candidate from that party with the most votes, assign the second seat to the candidate with the second-most votes, and so on. This allows the voters supporting each party to have a say in what candidates from that party get elected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last post, we went over an example election where the parties A, B, and C ran for 10 seats, and A was supported by 50 voters, B by 30 voters, and C by 20 voters. Closed party-list elected 5 A candidates, 3 B candidates, and 2 C candidates, thus giving a proportional outcome. Using D’Hondt will also result in this outcome, as is demonstrated by the table of vote counts below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Round&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;B&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;C&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;50&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;30&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;25&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;16.67&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;20&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;16.67&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;15&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;12.5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;10&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.33&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;10&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.33&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;10&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the party proportions are the same, the difference is that D’Hondt will ensure that the elected A candidates are the 5 A candidates with the most votes, and same for the other parties. D’Hondt also specifies how to deal with scenarios where perfect party proportionally is impossible without fractional seats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, this method gives voters strictly more choice than closed party-list did. However, it still limits voters to supporting a single candidate and a single party. In the next part, we’ll look at some proposals for altering this method to resolve this issue.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>The motivation behind SPSV, part 1</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/10/23/the-motivation-behind-spsv-part-1"/>
			<updated>2020-10-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/10/23/the-motivation-behind-spsv-part-1</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog post has been adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/SimDemocracy/comments/ieogtk/the_motivation_behind_spsv_series/&quot;&gt;a series of posts&lt;/a&gt; written for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/SimDemocracy/&quot;&gt;r/SimDemocracy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/miscellaneous/voting-theory/sequential-proportional-score-voting&quot;&gt;Sequential proportional score voting&lt;/a&gt; (SPSV) is a multi-winner voting method and a form of &lt;a href=&quot;https://electowiki.org/wiki/Proportional_representation&quot;&gt;proportional representation&lt;/a&gt;. Like score voting, it uses rated ballots, and it is party-agnostic, meaning it does not take into account which parties the candidates are from. Currently, the only known instance of this method being used is the subreddit r/SimDemocracy, which uses it to elect its legislature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before SimDemocracy used SPSV, it used a method known as bloc score. This method was simpler to understand, but it had major issues when it came to electing a senate that represents the voters. This occurred because it was not a proportional method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example of why proportionally is important, let’s consider an election with 3 parties: A, B, and C. A is supported by 50 voters, B by 30 voters, and C by 20 voters. For simplicity, we’ll say that there are 10 seats and each party runs 10 candidates. We’ll first consider this election under bloc score, and then we’ll consider it under closed party-list, a proportional method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under bloc score, voters rate each of the candidates, and the candidates with the highest total scores win. Since each voter supports exactly one party, we’ll assume that they give all candidates in that party the maximum rating, 5, and all other candidates the minimum rating, 0. This means that the A candidates each have 250 points, the B candidates 150 points, and the C candidates 100 points. Thus, bloc score will elect the 10 A candidates. This is clearly not representative; A has only 50% of the vote, but has total control over the elected body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closed party-list works very differently. Instead of rating candidates, voters cast their vote for a single party. Each party wins seats in proportion to how many votes they receive. In this case, A receives 50 votes, B receives 30 votes, and C receives 20 votes. Thus, closed party-list will elect 5 A candidates, 3 B candidates, and 2 C candidates. This results in the elected body having a makeup that closely resembles the makeup of the voters, and so is far more representative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While closed party-list gives far more representative outcomes than a non-proportional method like bloc score, it also has a lot of disadvantages. One is that voters don’t get any say over which candidates from a party are elected; instead, that’s determined by party insiders. SPSV is much better, but it’s easiest to build up to it rather than diving straight in. Thus, the next part will cover a proportional method very similar to closed party-list that lets voters choose which candidates are elected, and from there we’ll keep making small changes until we arrive at SPSV itself.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>The NPVIC, RCV-1, and Maine</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/08/10/the-npvic-rcv1-and-maine"/>
			<updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/08/10/the-npvic-rcv1-and-maine</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalpopularvote.com/&quot;&gt;National Popular Vote Interstate Compact&lt;/a&gt; (NPVIC) aims to subvert the Electoral College and elect the president of the U.S. by popular vote. It would accomplish this by having the states that signed on give their electoral votes to whichever candidate won the popular vote. However, the way it defines the popular vote assumes that all states will use single-choice plurality voting in their presidential elections. This is a problem, because &lt;a href=&quot;https://bangordailynews.com/2020/07/15/politics/maine-to-use-ranked-choice-voting-in-presidential-election-after-gop-veto-effort-fails/&quot;&gt;Maine has switched its presidential elections&lt;/a&gt; to use single-winner ranked choice voting (RCV-1), also known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Instant-runoff_voting&quot;&gt;instant runoff voting&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NPVIC website doesn’t address this possibility, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/EndFPTP/comments/9k7xpg/how_would_the_npvic_behave_if_a_state_chose_to/e6ypbs1/&quot;&gt;promoters have suggested&lt;/a&gt; that this problem would be resolved by the state explaining how its votes should be tallied. This is an unsatisfactory answer for a few reasons. First, there are multiple options for how the votes could be added. One option is to ignore the use of RCV-1 and simply count voters’ first preferences. Another option is to have Maine run RCV-1 until all but two candidates are eliminated, then count voters as having cast a plurality vote for whichever of those two candidates they preferred.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A third option is to hold a nationwide RCV-1 tally where voters from other states are considered to have cast ballots that ranked only one candidate. Each of these options has advantages that will appeal to some people and disadvantages that will drive others away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second reason why this isn’t a good solution is that it may not work if other states adopt other methods. This probably wouldn’t be an issue anytime soon; the most likely alternative to be adopted at the state level is approval voting, and there are options for &lt;a href=&quot;https://electowiki.org/wiki/Single_transferable_vote#Ways_of_dealing_with_equal_rankings&quot;&gt;adapting RCV-1 to work with equal rankings&lt;/a&gt;. However, in a scenario where other methods gain traction in the future, this could become very difficult. Trying to add RCV-1 ballots, &lt;a href=&quot;https://electowiki.org/wiki/3-2-1_voting&quot;&gt;3-2-1&lt;/a&gt; ballots, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ranked_pairs&quot;&gt;ranked pairs&lt;/a&gt; ballots together while respecting how those voting methods operate would be a nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final reason I don’t consider this solution to be enough is that it relies on the states agreeing on a method for adding the ballots together. If different states have different priorities, they may not be able to agree on a method. For instance, Maine may want to stay as true to its chosen voting method as possible, while other states may want a simple method that gives all voters the same options. Even if the states are cooperative with each other and try to find a compromise, the process could still take a lot of time. If it isn’t finished by the time the next presidential election is held, the election results could be severely delayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know what the future holds for the NPVIC. Maybe it will be unable to get enough states to pass it and simply die off. Maybe Maine will repeal RCV-1 and join the other states in sticking with single-choice plurality. Or maybe this problem will need to be dealt with at some point. If that becomes the case, things could become rather unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Voters who didn’t rank either of the two finalists would be considered to have abstained. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Quadratic voting and types of one person, one vote</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/08/09/quadratic-voting-and-types-of-one-person-one-vote"/>
			<updated>2020-08-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/08/09/quadratic-voting-and-types-of-one-person-one-vote</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02/16/the-meaning-of-one-person-one-vote&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I laid out a hierarchy of three different possible meanings of one person, one vote (OPOV). The 1st level of OPOV required that each voter have exactly one ballot. The 2nd level required that each ballot have the same weight. Finally, the 3rd level required each possible ballot to be perfectly cancelled out by another possible ballot. I also created a combination Euler/pyramid diagram to demonstrate the relationship visually:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/OPOV.png&quot; alt=&quot;One person, one vote diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before moving on, I’d like to formalize these types of OPOV a little more. I do think the 3rd level was defined well enough, but you can visit &lt;a href=&quot;/miscellaneous/voting-theory/cancellation-criterion&quot;&gt;this page for the cancellation criterion&lt;/a&gt; if you need a refresher. For the 2nd level, it might not always be clear when the “weights” of two ballots are equal. It turns out that this has already been formalized through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://electowiki.org/wiki/Neutrality_criterion&quot;&gt;anonymity criterion&lt;/a&gt;, which requires that for every fixed set of votes, the winner of the election remains the same regardless of which voters cast which of the votes from that set. This captures straightforward failure cases like the Electoral College, but also some stranger edge cases that might not have clear “weights” to compare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When considering the 1st level, we run into the issue of defining what counts as “one ballot”. For a rated method with a 0-5 scale, we could give a voter an unfair advantage by giving them two 0-5 ballots and adding them together. We could also give them an advantage by giving them a single 0-10 ballot. But mathematically, these two advantages are one and the same, even though supposedly one has two ballots and the other only one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can solve this by requiring ballots to provide the same set of options for casting a vote to each voter. Now the single 0-10 ballot still violates this, even if it wouldn’t under a more literal interpretation of “one ballot”. I decided to formalize this idea into the &lt;a href=&quot;/miscellaneous/voting-theory/identical-input-options-criterion&quot;&gt;identical input options (IIO) criterion&lt;/a&gt;. As a quick reality check, the IIO criterion is implied by the anonymity criterion, which means that any voting system&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; passing anonymity must also pass IIO. This matches up with the idea that any voting system with equally-weighted ballots should also have exactly one ballot per voter, as shown in the above diagram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve formalized the types of OPOV more, we can move on to the other portion of this post’s topic: &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2003531&quot;&gt;quadratic voting&lt;/a&gt;. Under quadratic voting, voters “buy” multiple points in favor of a single option using “voice credits”, and the option with the most points in favor wins. The cost of buying points for a given option is the square of the number of points being bought. This means that 1 point would cost 1 credit, 2 points would cost 4 credits, 3 points would cost 9 credits, and so on. Thus, the cost function ends up being quadratic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/quadratic-voting-cost.png&quot; alt=&quot;Graph showing the quadratic nature of the cost function&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous OPOV post, I said that quadratic voting failed every type of OPOV. This is true for the version I just described, but it turns out that there are variations of quadratic voting that can pass different types of OPOV. This makes quadratic voting a useful tool for explaining how voting systems can be altered to pass or fail the various types of OPOV. In particular, I want to consider the scenario of quadratic voting being used in U.S. presidential elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start off by considering the case where all states switch to using quadratic voting, but still operate within the Electoral College system. We’ll assume that the voice credits persist over multiple elections, possibly (but not necessarily) because they are real currency. This means that different voters will have different amounts of voice credits in each election, and so some voters will be able to cast votes that others won’t. For example, a voter with 10 voice credits could give Candidate A 3 points and Candidate B 1 point since 3&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; + 1&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; = 9 + 1 = 10. In contrast, a voter with only 9 voice credits would be unable to cast this vote. Thus, this system fails the IIO criterion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when we modify the system to distribute a fixed number of voice credits to each voter in each election, without the ability to save them for future elections? Well, we’ve eliminated the issue of different voters being able to cast different votes, so the IIO criterion is now passed.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, because the Electoral College is still in place, it remains possible to change the outcome of many elections by changing which voters cast which votes in each election. Thus, the anonymity criterion is still failed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modifying this system to pass the anonymity criterion is straightforward; all we need to do is replace the Electoral College with a national popular vote. Now every voter is treated the same regardless of what state they vote in, so there is no way to change the outcome of the election by swapping votes around. However, it’s not always possible for one voter to perfectly cancel out the vote of another voter. For example, if each voter is given 100 voice credits per election and there are three candidates A, B, and C, then one voter can cast a vote that gives 10 points to A. Perfectly cancelling this vote out would require giving 10 points to B and 10 points to C, but doing that would cost 200 voice credits, so any voter with only 100 voice credits couldn’t cast a cancelling vote. Thus, the cancellation criterion is still failed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point it might feel like we’ve modified quadratic voting to pass all the types of OPOV it possibly can. However, there is a way to modify it further so that it passes the cancellation criterion; instead of restricting voters to buying points in favor of an option, we also let them buy points in opposition to an option. This means that in the example above, the vote that gives 10 points in favor of A can now be cancelled by a vote that gives 10 points in opposition to A. In fact, it will always possible to construct a valid vote that cancels out another valid vote, as we can simply reverse whether the points purchased are in favor of or in opposition to each option. Thus, this version of quadratic voting passes the cancellation criterion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m hoping this demonstration of modifying a voting system to pass each type of OPOV in sequence helps build intuition for how the types relate to one another and to the voting systems that pass and fail them. If some of the vaguer types seemed arbitrary, I also hope that my efforts to provide more formal criteria helped clarify things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In both this post and the previous post on OPOV, I kind of conflate voting methods with electoral systems under the term “voting systems”. If this doesn’t bother you, you can just ignore it. If this does bother you, you can think about this matter purely in terms of electoral systems by applying a simple default electoral system as a “wrapper” around any voting methods that are mentioned. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This assumes that for each state, all candidates either make it onto the ballot or can be written in. If this doesn’t happen, then IIO is still violated. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Soul harvester</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/07/14/soul-harvester"/>
			<updated>2020-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/07/14/soul-harvester</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Epistemic status: fiction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people believe that the soul is the essence of a person. These people are wrong. The essence of a person is their consciousness, and consciousness is merely a complex and intricate set of computations occurring in the brain. The reason so many believe this myth regarding souls arises from the consequences of removing one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exact results vary from procedure to procedure, but what they all have in common is the destruction of the patient’s consciousness. In some cases the patient simply dies. In others they enter a permanent coma-like state. And for some procedures, the results are… best left unsaid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue that all of these procedures encounter is related to the soul’s dependence on a person’s consciousness. Without a consciousness to shape it, a soul would merely be a small and unremarkable reservoir of magical energy. However, magical energy shaped directly by consciousness becomes incredibly useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason souls are so valuable is that they can be used as oracle machines, which can perform feats that should be computationally impossible. Many of the most powerful spells and rituals are dependent on the ability to solve impossible computations, and thus require the use of a soul in order to be completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such spell is the Explorable Prophecy. This spell operates by simulating the counterfactual universe in which it has no effect, and then allowing the caster to explore this simulation as they please. Needless to say, this requires an incredible amount of computational power, assuming it is even computable at all. Without the existence of souls, casting a spell like this one would be entirely infeasible. With souls, this task becomes possible, albeit incredibly difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the utility of souls comes at a cost. The consciousness that shapes the soul does so in order to make use of its computational abilities. This was driven by evolution, but evolution is not intelligent, and so the brain does not use the soul anywhere near as effectively as it could. In fact, it does not even use it for anything it can’t do itself. But it does use the soul enough to become dependent on it. And so, if the soul is removed, the consciousness ceases to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except there was a case where this didn’t happen. I cannot divulge the specifics, but I can say that it inspired me to develop a new technique for removing souls. The key to this technique is to slowly disrupt the brain’s connection with the soul over a long period of time. The brain has enough plasticity to learn that it can no longer depend on the soul and eventually will fully take over. At this point, the soul can be removed without causing any harm to the patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going into further detail about the procedure would unfortunately require me to reveal proprietary information. However, I believe what I have divulged should be a satisfactory explanation of how my product can be ethically sourced.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Why 1 is not prime</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/07/05/why-1-is-not-prime"/>
			<updated>2020-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/07/05/why-1-is-not-prime</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Modern mathematicians have come to the consensus that the number 1 is not a prime number. However, many people still believe that 1 is in fact prime. This belief is justified by definitions like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a prime number is a positive whole number that is only divisible by 1 and itself&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and indeed, under this definition 1 would be prime. However, most definitions are worded to exclude 1, usually by specifying that a prime number must be greater than 1.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why make the definition more complicated just to prevent 1 from being a prime number? Wouldn’t it make more sense to just say it is prime? Well, it turns out that treating 1 as a prime number is quite awkward as it lacks many properties that all prime numbers have. This post will go over four of those properties, and in doing so will hopefully make the exclusion of 1 less of a mystery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first property is that prime numbers can only appear in an integer’s factorization finitely many times. For example, 64 can be written as 2&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;, but it cannot be written as 2&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;, 2&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;, or any other larger power of 2. This property is key to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fundamental_theorem_of_arithmetic&quot;&gt;Fundamental Theorem of Arithmetic&lt;/a&gt;, which states that every positive integer can be uniquely represented as a product of primes.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Thus, if you know an integer is equal to some product of primes, you also know that no other product of primes will be equal to that integer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we try to include 1 as a prime number, however, we run into a problem. Since 1 times any number equals that number, 1 can appear in a factorization an arbitrary number of times. As an example, 2 = 2 × 1 = 2 × 1 × 1 = 2 × 1 × 1 × 1 and so on. This means that counting 1 as a prime number breaks the Fundamental Theorem of Arithmetic, and in order to get it back we have to explicitly exclude 1 from the list of prime factors that the theorem applies to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fundamental Theorem of Arithmetic is probably the most-often cited reason for why 1 isn’t prime, but on its own it may not seem to be a sufficient justification. However, there are other properties that primes have and 1 lacks. For instance, the multiples of a prime that are greater than the prime itself are all composite numbers. This fact is exploited by an algorithm for finding primes up to some limit known as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sieve_of_Eratosthenes&quot;&gt;sieve of Eratosthenes&lt;/a&gt;. It works by finding the first prime it has yet to find, then marking all multiples of it as composite. It can then skip over those numbers when finding the next prime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we start the sieve of Eratosthenes at 2, everything works fine. In contrast, if we start it at 1, it immediately marks all other numbers as composite and declares 1 to be the only prime. Since all primes (and all other positive integers) are multiples of 1, the strategy employed by the sieve of Eratosthenes cannot work. Instead, it would need to be modified to skip the step of marking multiples as composite for 1. Again, we find ourselves needing to make special accommodations for 1 if we consider it to be prime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another instance in which including 1 as a prime creates a problem is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler%27s_totient_function&quot;&gt;Euler’s totient function&lt;/a&gt;. This function takes in a positive integer &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; and outputs the number of totatives &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; has, where a totative of &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; is a positive integer &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; ≤ &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; where the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greatest_common_divisor&quot;&gt;greatest common divisor&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; is 1. That may feel like a lot to take in, so let’s go through an example. Consider &lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;(6), where &lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt; is Euler’s totient function. To find the value of this expression, we need to find all the totatives of 6. Starting with 1, we find that gcd(1, 6) = 1, so 1 is a totative of 6. In the case of 2, gcd(2, 6) = 2, so 2 is not a totative of 6. As for the rest, gcd(3, 6) = 3, gcd(4, 6) = 2, gcd(5, 6) = 1, and gcd(6, 6) = 6. Thus, 5 is the only other totative of 6, and &lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;(6) = 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may have guessed, prime numbers have a unique property that involves Euler’s totient function. Specifically, for any prime number &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;) = &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; - 1. This arises from the fact that &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; only has two factors, 1 and &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;. This means that gcd(&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;) equals &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; when &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; is a multiple of &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; and 1 otherwise. For &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; ≤ &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;, the only &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; that’s a multiple of &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; itself. Thus, every other &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; will be a totative of &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When calculating &lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;(1), there is only a single value of &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; to consider, namely 1. It so happens that gcd(1, 1) = 1, so 1 is a totative of 1 and &lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;(1) = 1. Once again, this does not fit the pattern that the prime numbers follow. Thus, if we include 1 as a prime, we must amend our statement to say that for any prime number &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; except 1, &lt;em&gt;φ&lt;/em&gt;(&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;) = &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; - 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with Euler’s totient function, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Divisor_function&quot;&gt;sum-of-divisors function&lt;/a&gt; also highlights a property of primes that 1 lacks. The sum-of-divisors function, referred to as σ, takes a positive integer as input and outputs the sum of all its positive divisors. For instance, 12 has 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, and 12 as divisors, so σ(12) = 1 + 2 + 3 + 4 + 6 + 12 = 28. As we’ve said before, a prime number &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; has only two divisors, 1 and &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;, so it’s easy to see that σ(&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;) = &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; + 1 for any prime number. As has become quite predictable by now, 1 fails to follow this pattern. It only has a single divisor, 1, so σ(1) = 1 rather than 2 as it would if it followed the pattern.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I have succeeded in giving a more satisfying explanation of why 1 isn’t prime than whichever one (ha!)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; you knew of before. This was one of those aspects of math that seemed weirdly arbitrary to me when I was younger, and I am quite thankful to have a better understanding of why prime numbers are defined the way they are. The reasons for this go far beyond what I have discussed here, but I think the examples I chose do a decent job of balancing insight with simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Some definitions instead say that prime numbers have exactly two positive integer factors, which I find to be a much more natural means of excluding 1 from the primes. Nonetheless, requiring primes to be greater than 1 seems to be more common; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prime_number&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wolframalpha.com/examples/mathematics/number-theory/prime-numbers/&quot;&gt;Wolfram|Alpha&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathworld.wolfram.com/PrimeNumber.html&quot;&gt;Wolfram &lt;em&gt;MathWorld&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; all use this option. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This assumes that the use of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Empty_product&quot;&gt;empty product&lt;/a&gt; is allowed. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This failure can be actually be generalized to a whole set of divisor functions. Let &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; through &lt;em&gt;d&lt;sub&gt;k&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt; represent the &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; divisors of &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;. Define σ&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;(&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;) = &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;x&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;x&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; + ⋯ + &lt;em&gt;d&lt;sub&gt;k&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;x&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Then for any prime number &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;, σ&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;(&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;) = &lt;em&gt;p&lt;sup&gt;x&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; + 1. In contrast, σ&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;(1) = 1. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’m sorry. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Thanos is a straw centrist</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/04/01/thanos-is-a-straw-centrist"/>
			<updated>2020-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/04/01/thanos-is-a-straw-centrist</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A straw centrist is a person who always takes the middle position on issues. For example, if you asked them if we should kill all the men or not, they would say that we should kill half of the men. If you asked them if we should kill all the women or not, they would say that we should kill half of the women. And if you asked them if we should kill all the children or not, they would say that we should kill half of the children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it wouldn’t just be disjoint groups for which this is true. If you asked them if we should kill all the teachers or not, they would say that we should kill half of them. But how could they make sure that they don’t accidentally kill over half of the teachers while killing half of the women? Well, by the law of large numbers, there is a really simple method to ensure that they kill half of every group: choose a random sample to kill. If the sample size is equal to the size of half of the population, then they will achieve all of their goals at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we see how Thanos qualifies as a straw centrist: his plan is exactly what we’d expect from one. This also explains why he talks about balance all the time. A straw centrist picks the middle position on every issue because they want to balance the advantages and disadvantages of each side. In the same way, Thanos kills half the population because he wants to balance the advantages and disadvantages of killing everyone and killing no one. Therefore, it’s safe to conclude that Thanos is indeed a straw centrist.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>The meaning of one person, one vote</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/02/16/the-meaning-of-one-person-one-vote"/>
			<updated>2020-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2020/02/16/the-meaning-of-one-person-one-vote</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The concept of one person, one vote is often brought up in discussions of voting methods and electoral systems. In the United States, it’s commonly associated with a Supreme Court decision that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/one-person_one-vote_rule&quot;&gt;required states to use districts with approximately equal populations&lt;/a&gt;. However, the general idea that everyone’s vote should be equal has been brought up as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pressherald.com/2018/05/30/commentary-one-person-one-vote-at-risk-if-ranked-choice-voting-approved/&quot;&gt;way&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/ukpolitics/comments/a5t0co/comment/ebozc6n/&quot;&gt;challenge&lt;/a&gt; alternative voting methods like approval voting and instant-runoff voting (abbreviated IRV, and also called ranked-choice voting), despite the fact that votes cast under these methods &lt;a href=&quot;https://ivn.us/2018/12/04/ranked-choice-voting-survives-one-person-one-vote-challenge/&quot;&gt;are not&lt;/a&gt; any &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.electionscience.org/voting-methods/ten-critiques-and-defenses-on-approval-voting/&quot;&gt;less equal&lt;/a&gt; than the single-choice plurality method used in most U.S. elections. To make this even more complicated, this concept has also been used to argue in favor of replacing plurality voting with alternative methods. The Equal Vote Coalition’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equal.vote/theequalvote&quot;&gt;equality criterion&lt;/a&gt; is a good example of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having all these overlapping concepts associated with one phrase is likely to lead to a lot of confusion. For instance, Equal Vote appears to equivocate between two different meanings in their page &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equal.vote/star-vs-irv#equality&quot;&gt;comparing STAR and IRV&lt;/a&gt;. The section on equality begins with the following sentence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The U.S. Supreme Court has found unequivocally that ‘One Person, One Vote’ requires that “each vote be given as much weight as any other vote.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the page goes on to claim that IRV fails one person, one vote, which is not true under the Supreme Court’s definition. Instead, Equal Vote has switched to applying their own equality criterion. Without proper clarification, this is very misleading to readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help counter the confusion that can arise in this and similar situations, I’d like to construct a hierarchy of the various interpretations of one person, one vote. This hierarchy will have 3 levels, with each successive level being more restrictive than the last. Thus, passing the 2nd level means the 1st level is also passed, and meeting the 3rd level ensures that both other levels are satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1st level is the most literal interpretation of one person, one vote. It simply requires that every participant gets exactly one ballot. This is the version that some attempt to employ against methods like approval and IRV; their mistake is that they conceive of a vote as being a mark on a ballot rather than the ballot itself. When the latter conception of a vote is used, it becomes clear that pretty much any serious voting system passes this level of one person, one vote. However, an interesting exception to this is &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2003531&quot;&gt;quadratic voting&lt;/a&gt;, which allows voters to “buy” multiple votes on a single issue using “voice credits”.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2nd level of one person, one vote requires that every voter’s ballot be weighted equally. This is the interpretation used by the U.S. Supreme Court to eliminate unequally-sized districts at the state level, including a pair of districts where 41 times as many voters lived in one district as did in the other. Pretty much all voting systems satisfy this requirement, assuming they use districts of roughly equal size. Alternatively, the number of representatives for a district can be kept proportional to the number of voters in that district. Note that the Electoral College fails to do this, so it does not satisfy this level of one person, one vote.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 3rd and strictest level of one person, one vote is the previously mentioned equality criterion, also referred to as Frohnmayer balance. The Equal Vote Coalition &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equal.vote/theequalvote&quot;&gt;describes&lt;/a&gt; this criterion as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A voting method passes the Equality Criterion if every possible vote expression has a counter-balancing vote expression &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; if the counting system produces the same election outcome when any pairing of a vote expression and its counter-balancing vote expression are added to the tally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, when one person casts a vote, it must always be possible for another person to cast a vote that will perfectly cancel it out, regardless of how all other votes are cast. This is actually far more restrictive than the previous levels of one person, one vote. For instance, single-choice plurality voting fails this criterion, as does the popular reform option instant-runoff voting. It’s also &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.electionscience.org/t/interpretations-of-one-person-one-vote/299/2&quot;&gt;impossible&lt;/a&gt; for any multi-winner voting method that achieves proportional representation to pass this criterion.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the few voting methods that do meet this criterion are approval voting, score voting, and STAR voting. To cancel out a vote when using approval voting, you simply approve all the candidates that weren’t approved on the other ballot. This results in each candidate receiving exactly one approval from the two ballots, keeping the differences between their totals the same. Under score and STAR, you have to give the candidates the ratings opposite of those on the other ballot. For example, using a scale from 0-5, a rating of 5 would be canceled with a rating of 0, a rating of 4 would be canceled with a rating of 1, etc. This ensures that the two ballots give each candidate exactly 5 points total. In the case of STAR, it also preserves pairwise results, so the winner of the automatic runoff will remain the same as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize, the 1st level of one person, one vote requires that each voter have exactly one ballot. The 2nd level requires that each ballot have the same weight. The 3rd level requires that each possible ballot can be perfectly cancelled out by another possible ballot. To illustrate this relationship, I’ve created a helpful combination Euler/pyramid diagram:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/OPOV.png&quot; alt=&quot;One person, one vote diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It’s called “quadratic voting” because the number of credits needed to buy votes for a given issue is the square of the number of votes being bought (so 1 vote costs 1 credit, 2 votes cost 4 credits, 3 votes cost 9 credits, and so on). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The U.S. Supreme Court’s interpretation of one person, one vote only applies to the states, so there’s no constitutional issue here. In fact, the Electoral College system doesn’t even require states to hold elections to decide how to choose their electors. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There is a proposal for a similarly strict version of one person, one vote that can be passed by proportional methods called &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.electionscience.org/t/different-reweighting-for-rrv-and-the-concept-of-vote-unitarity/201&quot;&gt;Vote Unitarity&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>On normative ethical theories</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2019/04/01/on-normative-ethical-theories"/>
			<updated>2019-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2019/04/01/on-normative-ethical-theories</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scedastic/status/1036625675866791939&quot;&gt;this tweet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Normative_ethics#Normative_ethical_theories&quot;&gt;a lot of proposals&lt;/a&gt; for what makes an action morally good or bad. These normative ethical theories can take various forms, but the most plausible are types of utilitarianism. This is because utilitarianism allows agents that follow it to behave rationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Von_Neumann%E2%80%93Morgenstern_utility_theorem&quot;&gt;von Neumann-Morgenstern utility theorem&lt;/a&gt; shows that any agent that does not behave as if it has a utility function can have arbitrary amounts of resources pumped from it. This is a huge problem for any normative ethical theory that does not allow agents to behave this way. “Moral” agents would be unable to reliably perform obviously good acts like life-saving surgery because another agent could come along at any time and trick them into giving up the surgery equipment or other necessary resources. Since this is intuitively not how morality works, morality must be some form of utilitarianism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this mean that other theories are doomed? Not necessarily. It turns out that a lot of them can be easily converted into utilitarianism. For example, virtue ethics can be converted simply by holding &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scedastic/status/1036625675866791939&quot;&gt;“being as utilitarian as possible”&lt;/a&gt; as the only virtue worth having. Deontology can be similarly converted by making “act as a utilitarian would” the only rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other theories are much harder to convert. Contractarianism requires that everyone agree to a specific social contract, so if this contract is not already equivalent to some form of utilitarianism, then it would have to be “renegotiated”. This would be a daunting task, as it would require every single member of society to consent to a new utilitarian contract. Luckily, &lt;a href=&quot;http://econdse.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/Harsanyi_JPolE_55.pdf&quot;&gt;making a few reasonable assumptions&lt;/a&gt; allows us to show that we must have a social welfare function that consists of a weighted sum of individual utility functions. Since this is itself a utility function, this ensures that the social contract is indeed utilitarian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are not the only normative ethical theories in existence. There are plenty of others which should be examined for possible equivalences to utilitarianism and discarded if they are not found to have any. Of course, it’s also acceptable to simply apply utilitarianism directly rather than through some other theory, but having different ways to frame the matter is useful for making things as intuitive as possible. This might ultimately reach a point where all normative ethical theories are either unified in this way or dismissed as irrelevant, but until then, we must make do with the equivalences we have.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>The world's problems</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/12/31/the-worlds-problems"/>
			<updated>2018-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/12/31/the-worlds-problems</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of problems out there. Some of these problems are small, like whether you should get a new phone or not. Other problems are big, like how to solve climate change. But of these problems, which ones are the most important? I don’t know, of course, but I’m going to hazard a guess at them anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a quick overview of the criteria I’m using to determine importance.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I’ll be considering the impact, tractability, and neglectedness of problems. Impact is simply how good solving the problem would be. Tractability is how easy it is to make progress on the problem; if all else is equal, directing the same amount of resources to a more tractable problem will result in more good being done. Neglectedness is how few people and resources are being directed at the problem. Due to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/l/lawofdiminishingmarginalreturn.asp&quot;&gt;the law of diminishing returns&lt;/a&gt;, a more neglected problem will generally be easier to make progress on than a less neglected one.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current guess for the 5th most important problem is poverty, which I believe can be most effectively solved through &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unconditional_cash_transfer&quot;&gt;unconditional cash transfers&lt;/a&gt;. In developing countries, this would involve performing the work of charities like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly&lt;/a&gt;. For developed countries, the goal would be the implementation of policies like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_income&quot;&gt;universal basic income&lt;/a&gt;, which provides regular cash transfers to every citizen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d expect solving this well to have a large positive impact by reducing human suffering and giving many people an opportunity to contribute to society that they would have otherwise been denied. The simplicity of unconditional cash transfers would make the problem very tractable. As for neglectedness, few charities are working on this, and no country has yet to implement a full UBI. If you’re interested in further reading on why these options might be worth supporting, I’d suggest starting with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givewell.org/international/technical/programs/cash-transfers&quot;&gt;GiveWell’s page on cash transfers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scottsantens.com/basic-income-faq&quot;&gt;Scott Santens’ basic income FAQ&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving information aggregation occupies the 4th spot on my list of problems. Thanks to the internet, access to information is no longer a problem for most people. However, it often remains difficult to determine the accuracy of a given piece of information, or to properly combine small bits of evidence to reach a solid conclusion. One technology that could help with this in many circumstances is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prediction_market&quot;&gt;prediction markets&lt;/a&gt;. Prediction markets operate via “stocks” that pay out a certain amount only if a certain event happens. Thus, the price of one of these financial instruments as a percentage of the payout amount is the probability of the event happening, according to the market. For example, if an instrument pays out $100 if Trump is reelected in 2020 and it’s trading for $38, then the market currently believes there’s a 38% chance of Trump’s reelection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact of improving information aggregation would be huge, as the decision-making processes of organizations from corporations to governments would receive a substantial boost. The main issue is that popularizing prediction markets seems like a rather intractable problem, especially given that online prediction markets are effectively outlawed in the United States. On the other hand, very few people are working on this issue, and it may be the most neglected problem on this list. For additional reading on how prediction markets could be directly incorporated into a governance structure, see &lt;a href=&quot;http://mason.gmu.edu/~rhanson/futarchy.html&quot;&gt;Robin Hanson’s futarchy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 3rd position goes to the problem of aggregating values. The largest improvement here was the invention of democracy, but there’s still much room to do better. The most common voting method, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plurality_voting&quot;&gt;single-choice plurality voting&lt;/a&gt;, is generally agreed to be one of the worst voting methods in existence. It’s highly inexpressive, and it falls prey to vote-splitting and spoilers, which makes it hard for new candidates to run, increases polarization, and forces strategic voters to vote dishonestly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact of improving value aggregation through a better voting method is quite large, as can be seen in the available improvements in &lt;a href=&quot;https://electology.github.io/vse-sim/VSE/&quot;&gt;voter satisfaction efficiency&lt;/a&gt; under alternative methods. &lt;a href=&quot;https://electology.org/blog/fargo-nd-becomes-first-us-city-adopt-approval-voting-landslide-win&quot;&gt;Current voting reform efforts&lt;/a&gt; suggest that this is a fairly tractable problem as well. And while it’s not the least neglected problem, there seem to be few people pushing the best reforms available. For further reading, I’d start with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/s/ZBNBTSMAXbyJwJoKY/p/D6trAzh6DApKPhbv4&quot;&gt;this introduction to voting theory&lt;/a&gt;, which is how I was first introduced to the subject.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2nd entry on the list is home to the problem of identifying important problems. It turns out that doing this is really hard, and a lot of groups have put a whole lot more effort into this than I have. Unfortunately, these groups tend to end up generating &lt;a href=&quot;https://borgenproject.org/world-issues/&quot;&gt;very&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://80000hours.org/articles/cause-selection/&quot;&gt;different&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gviusa.com/blog/6-critical-global-issues-what-are-the-worlds-biggest-problems-and-how-i-can-help/&quot;&gt;lists&lt;/a&gt;, likely in part because they use different criteria. Given that it is pretty hard to make progress on important problems if you don’t know what the important problems are, this seems like a pressing issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identifying important problems would likely have a very large impact through shifting efforts from less important problems to more important ones. It appears to be somewhat tractable given the existing progress that has been made. Since people generally pick a cause to focus on without checking how well it meets these criteria, this should be a rather neglected problem as well. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.effectivealtruism.org/&quot;&gt;effective altruism movement&lt;/a&gt; is an excellent place to start looking into this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only problem I find more important than identifying important problems is that of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.existential-risk.org/faq.html&quot;&gt;existential risks&lt;/a&gt;. While it is difficult to make progress on important problems if you don’t know what they are, it is impossible to make progress on them if humanity is extinct or otherwise incapable of realizing a better future. Given &lt;a href=&quot;https://nickbostrom.com/astronomical/waste.html&quot;&gt;the astronomical amount of potential good&lt;/a&gt; that could be realized in the future, this would be an unacceptable loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consider preserving the possibility of a good future to be one of the highest impact actions there is. Unfortunately, it’s likely one of the less tractable problems on this list, as reliably affecting the far future seems to be a difficult task. Existential risk is a very neglected problem, however, so there should still be ways to improve the situation. If you’re interested, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://futureoflife.org/&quot;&gt;Future of Life Institute&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fhi.ox.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;Future of Humanity Institute&lt;/a&gt; have some great resources on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One aspect of these problems that I find quite fascinating is how solving one can help with solving others. Someone lifted out of poverty by cash transfers may go on to discover the importance of a problem that would have otherwise gone unnoticed. Prediction markets could help identify which voting methods outperform others in specific circumstances. And preventing existential catastrophes ensures that we retain the opportunity to fix all of these other problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These kinds of relationships should not be too surprising; it makes perfect sense that more important problems would have many indirect effects on other problems. Of course, just because these are important problems does not mean they are the most important problems, and I expect to change my mind on some of these in the future. In particular, I feel fairly uncertain about whether eliminating poverty and aggregating information should be on this list. I’m thinking I might write a post at the end of every year giving my updated positions on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;These criteria come from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://concepts.effectivealtruism.org/concepts/importance-neglectedness-tractability/&quot;&gt;effective altruism movement&lt;/a&gt;, though I won’t be applying them as rigorously here as others might elsewhere. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A more neglected problem will also generally have less people advocating for it, which in turn means you’re less likely to have heard of it. If my choice of problems seems weird to you, there’s a good chance that this is the reason. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Technically my first introduction was probably CGP Grey’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL7679C7ACE93A5638&quot;&gt;Politics in the Animal Kingdom series&lt;/a&gt;, but “single-choice voting is bad” is about all I took away from it at the time. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Ranked choice voting is worth supporting</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/11/26/ranked-choice-voting-is-worth-supporting"/>
			<updated>2018-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/11/26/ranked-choice-voting-is-worth-supporting</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ballotpedia.org/Ranked-choice_voting_(RCV)&quot;&gt;Ranked choice voting (RCV)&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fairvote.org/rcv#where_is_ranked_choice_voting_used&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rcvmaine.com/&quot;&gt;lot&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.voterchoicema.org/about_rcv&quot;&gt;of&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://act.represent.us/sign/ranked-choice-voting/&quot;&gt;supporters&lt;/a&gt; in the U.S. voting reform movement. However, the single-winner version, which also goes by the name instant-runoff voting (IRV), does have some detractors, particularly among those who support rated voting methods instead. Most still agree that RCV is an improvement over the single-choice voting method&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; used in almost every U.S. election, but a few dispute even this. While I believe that RCV is likely not the best single-winner method, I also believe that it is an improvement over single-choice voting. As such, I think you should support RCV even if you agree with many of the arguments made against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first argument I will address is RCV’s failure of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JtKAScORevQ&quot;&gt;the favorite betrayal criterion&lt;/a&gt;. The favorite betrayal criterion requires that a voting method never allows a voter to get a worse result by giving their favorite candidate maximum support. RCV’s failure of this criterion means there are situations in which a strategic voter will “betray” their favorite candidate by ranking them lower than another candidate. In other words, a voter’s favorite candidate may sometimes act as a spoiler that must be ranked lower than a more viable candidate in order to avoid the voter’s least-preferred outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait, doesn’t RCV &lt;a href=&quot;http://archive3.fairvote.org/reforms/instant-runoff-voting/irv-and-the-status-quo/spoiler-effect/&quot;&gt;eliminate the spoiler effect&lt;/a&gt;? Well, it depends on what you count as a spoiler. If you’re only concerned with scenarios where a minor candidate with only a few percent of the vote changes which of two major candidates wins, then yes, RCV eliminates spoilers. But if you also want to take into account scenarios where this candidate builds up enough support to beat the most similar major candidate, only to lose to the other major candidate, then RCV fails to eliminate all spoilers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it’s important to keep in mind that single-choice voting doesn’t eliminate any of these spoilers. So if you’re deciding between it and RCV, it’s hard to argue that RCV is worse because it fails the favorite betrayal criterion and allows spoilers. After all, single-choice voting also fails the favorite betrayal criterion and allows even more spoilers! Therefore, while this may be relevant when comparing RCV with other voting methods, it cannot serve as a reason why RCV is worse than single-choice voting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another argument made against RCV is that it is &lt;a href=&quot;https://electology.org/monotonicity&quot;&gt;non-monotonic&lt;/a&gt;. This means that there exist RCV elections in which it is possible for a winner to become a loser by receiving more support or vice versa. For example, consider these two scenarios involving candidates A, B, and C:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;overflow-x:auto;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;table&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Number of Voters&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Rankings&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Number of Voters&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Rankings&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;A &amp;gt; B &amp;gt; C&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;A &amp;gt; B &amp;gt; C&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;B &amp;gt; C &amp;gt; A&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;B &amp;gt; C &amp;gt; A&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;C &amp;gt; A &amp;gt; B&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;C &amp;gt; A &amp;gt; B&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first election, A is eliminated in the first round, and B goes on to win 11 to 6. In the second election, two of the voters who ranked B last in the first election have switched to ranking B first, increasing support for B. However, when the results are found, C is eliminated in the first round, and then A wins 9 to 8!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This behavior is a problem because it seems impossible to justify both outcomes. If it is correct for B to win the first election, then if support increases for B but not the other candidates, surely it must be correct for B to win the second election. Likewise, if it is correct for B to lose the second election, then if support decreases for B but not the other candidates, it intuitively must be correct for B to lose the first election. Thus, for every non-monotonic pair of elections, at least one outcome is incorrect. This implies that at least 50% of non-monotonic elections&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; choose the wrong candidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, to know how much of an effect non-monotonicity has, we also need to know the frequency of non-monotonic elections. &lt;a href=&quot;https://rangevoting.org/IrvParadoxProbabilities.html#SummTable&quot;&gt;Estimates for this&lt;/a&gt; show anywhere between 5% and 16% of elections to be non-monotonic. Even worse, when elections where RCV gives the same result as single-choice voting are excluded, estimates jump to between 9% and 36% of elections being non-monotonic. Compare this to single-choice voting, which is a monotonic method and therefore has a 0% rate of non-monotonicity. It seems like non-monotonicity succeeds as an argument against replacing single-choice voting with RCV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this argument ignores bad election results that arise for reasons other than non-monotonicity. If you really want to assess the accuracy of a voting method, you’ll need to be much more thorough. Luckily, there’s a way to do this called &lt;a href=&quot;https://electology.github.io/vse-sim/VSE/&quot;&gt;Voter Satisfaction Efficiency (VSE)&lt;/a&gt;. VSE is calculated by running tons of simulated elections and determining how satisfied voters are as a group with each result. A VSE score of 100% means the voting method always picks the candidate that maximizes voter satisfaction, and a VSE score of 0% means the voting method maximizes voter satisfaction as poorly as randomly selecting a candidate would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RCV earns VSE scores between 79% and 92%, depending on how strategic voters are. However, single-choice voting only earns between 71% and 86%. This means that despite being monotonic, single-choice voting fails to match RCV’s performance when it comes to voter satisfaction. RCV is simply a more accurate method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most concerning argument against RCV is that it risks “poisoning the well” for voting reform. Even though it performs better than single-choice voting, problems like non-monotonicity giving unintuitive results may lead to RCV being repealed. When a method that doesn’t have these problems is proposed by a different group of reformers, voters will choose to vote it down since they have no reason to believe this group of reformers has a better proposal than the last one did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t entirely hypothetical. There have been several instances where RCV &lt;a href=&quot;https://electology.org/irv-repealed&quot;&gt;has been repealed&lt;/a&gt;, and it intuitively seems like it would be bad strategy to try pushing another voting method in any of those cities. However, an important component of why this seems like a bad strategy is that there would be many other places to try this instead. This suggests that the actual damage that RCV would cause to the movement would be minimal, since you can always just go somewhere RCV hasn’t been tried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there is a very real risk that opposing a method as popular among reformers as RCV is could tear apart the voting reform movement. In my opinion, the worst-case scenario for the movement is that it splits into pro-RCV and anti-RCV factions that each actively oppose the method(s) preferred by their counterpart. In this “nightmare scenario”, the factions’ fights with each other make it easy for those who benefit from single-choice voting to keep it in place, since they can always get help from one faction to fight the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may strike many as an outlandish scenario, and I hope that it is in fact that improbable. But at the very least, I fear that some less extreme scenario could actually occur and make reform that much more difficult. And we desperately need reform right now. So for the sake of ending single-choice voting, I ask that you support RCV, even if, like me, you don’t think it’s the best option out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one final point I’d like to make. Most campaigns for voting reform are currently occurring at the local level, and those that aren’t are still only at the state level. There’s currently plenty of room for multiple methods to coexist. Supporting RCV does not meaningfully decrease the opportunities available to promote your favorite method. As long as this remains the case, maintaining unity is more important than implementing the absolute best method on every occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you weren’t willing to support RCV before, I hope I’ve convinced you to start doing so, if only grudgingly. Right now our focus needs to be on replacing single-choice voting; the voting reform movement can figure out what the optimal voting method is as we acquire more data on how well these methods behave in actual U.S. elections. In the meantime, continue advocating for your favorite method(s), but be sure to support other reformers’ favorite methods at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This method is commonly called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First-past-the-post_voting&quot;&gt;first-past-the-post voting&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plurality_voting&quot;&gt;plurality voting&lt;/a&gt;, but I’m avoiding those terms because it’s generally not obvious what they refer to. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Technically, non-monotonicity is a property of voting methods and pairs of elections, but not individual elections. However, the phrase “non-monotonic election” is often used as shorthand for “election in a non-monotonic pair of elections”, which is how I’m using it here. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>STAR voting in an interstate compact</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/10/14/star-voting-in-an-interstate-compact"/>
			<updated>2018-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/10/14/star-voting-in-an-interstate-compact</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jameson Quinn &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.electorama.com/wiki/3-2-1_voting#For_US_presidential_elections&quot;&gt;lays out a proposal&lt;/a&gt; for an interstate compact that links the result of the US presidential election to the national popular vote, similar to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalpopularvote.com/&quot;&gt;National Popular Vote Interstate Compact&lt;/a&gt;. However, unlike the NPVIC, this compact is designed to support not just &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plurality_voting&quot;&gt;plurality voting&lt;/a&gt;, but other voting methods as well. Specifically, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Approval_voting&quot;&gt;approval&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Score_voting&quot;&gt;score&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.electorama.com/wiki/3-2-1_voting&quot;&gt;3-2-1&lt;/a&gt; are all compatible.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Two notable methods are missing from this list: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Instant-runoff_voting&quot;&gt;instant-runoff voting&lt;/a&gt;, supported by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fairvote.org/&quot;&gt;FairVote&lt;/a&gt; (though under the name ranked choice voting), and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/STAR_voting&quot;&gt;STAR voting&lt;/a&gt;, supported by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.equal.vote/&quot;&gt;The Equal Vote Coalition&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For reasons I won’t go into here, I am more interested in STAR. Thus, I chose to work on extending the proposal to work with it. Since STAR and 3-2-1 are both rated runoff methods, I decided that it made sense to start with the procedure for 3-2-1 and modify it to fit STAR. The procedure I came up with is simply an addition to step 3 of the proposal, and works as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step 3: Possibly looking at the raw totals of other states, each state publishes its final totals. For a state using STAR, two finalists are first found by converting the raw totals into scores from 0 to 1 and selecting the two candidates with the highest average scores. Raw totals are converted as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plurality – the candidate voted for receives 1 point, and all others receive 0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Approval – approved candidates receive 1 point, and all others receive 0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Score – the minimum score is subtracted from all scores, which are then divided by the new maximum score&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;STAR – same process as score&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3-2-1 – “good” ratings are 1 point, “OK” ratings are 0.5 points, and “bad” ratings are 0 points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the finalists are selected, final local totals are generated for each candidate. For each STAR ballot, 1 point is awarded to the highest-rated finalist (or both if tied) as well as any higher-rated candidates. Other candidates rated the same or lower (including the lower-rated finalist, if there is one) receive 0 points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While step 3 was the only one to require any alterations, it was the longest step by far even before the STAR-specific instructions are added. It’s also the step that’s hardest to get right. Quinn gave a list of 4 criteria that the final local totals and the procedure that generates them should meet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each individual local ballot contributes between 0 and 1 points to each candidate’s final local tally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A ballot will always contribute 1 point to its most-preferred candidate and 0 points to its least-preferred candidate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A ballot will never contribute more points to a less-preferred candidate than to a more-preferred one.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If all states used the same final local tally procedure, the winner would be the STAR winner.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first criterion is obviously met since every candidate receives exactly 0 points or 1 point. The second criterion is met so long as it does not require all most-preferred and least-preferred candidates to receive the same number of points in the event of ties. The third criterion is met because all candidates receiving a score above that of the highest-rated finalist earn 1 point, and all candidates receiving a score below that of the highest-rated finalist earn 0 points. Unfortunately, the fourth criterion is not met by this procedure, as shown by this counterexample:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;overflow-x:auto;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;table&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Number of Voters&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Candidate A&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Candidate B&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Candidate C&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Candidate A receives 22 points, Candidate B receives 23 points, and Candidate C receives 16 points, so A and B are the finalists. A is favored over B on 5 ballots while B is favored over A on 6 ballots, so B is the winner under STAR. However, the procedure I specified assigns 6 points to A, 7 points to B, and 8 points to C, so C ends up being the winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that makes this example weird is that half the voters only rated candidates 0, 1, or 2, and thus only employed half of the available range of scores. Unfortunately, assuming all voters use the full range of their ballot does not prevent this problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;overflow-x:auto;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;table&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Number of Voters&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Candidate A&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Candidate B&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Candidate C&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Candidate D&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example, every voter rates at least one candidate 0 and at least one candidate 5. Candidate A receives 62 points, Candidate B receives 63 points, Candidate C receives 56 points, and Candidate D receives 55 points, so A and B are still the finalists. A is favored over B on 13 ballots while B is favored over A on 14 ballots, so B is the STAR winner. My procedure assigns 14 points to A, 15 points to B, 16 points to C, and 15 points to D, so under it C is the winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under what circumstances does this procedure deviate from simple STAR voting? Well, the first step will select the same finalists since the ratings are altered in a way that preserves the relative differences between their sums, then added and compared as in STAR. For the second step, STAR effectively awards points to the finalists in the same way that my procedure does.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, unlike my procedure, STAR never awards any points to non-finalists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since finalists are awarded points in the same way, the finalist that loses under STAR will never win under this procedure. However, a non-finalist might win if they are higher-rated than both finalists on over half the ballots. This is because every ballot assigns a point to at least one finalist, so at least one finalist will earn points from half the ballots or more. Thus, to beat this finalist, the non-finalist will have to be rated higher than both finalists on over half the ballots, since this is the only way the non-finalist can earn points from over half the ballots. This implies that failure to choose the STAR winner is rare, since this situation should not arise often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can derive a couple interesting properties from this information. First of all, a non-finalist winner will necessarily beat both finalists in pairwise matchups. Since a finalist winner necessarily beats the other finalist in a pairwise matchup, this means that my procedure never elects the Condorcet loser. It also means that for 3 candidate elections, the winner under my procedure will always be either the STAR winner or the Condorcet winner. This does not hold for 4 or more candidates; in the second example I gave, D is the Condorcet winner, not C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, all of this assumes that every state is using this procedure, which implies that all states have chosen to use STAR voting. In that case, it should be easy to amend the interstate compact to simply calculate the national STAR vote if that is desirable. What’s more relevant is what happens when this procedure is used alongside the procedures for other voting methods, which is what the first three criteria cover. Thus, I chose to prioritize meeting them over the last criterion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I feel this is reasonable for a first version of an extension of Quinn’s proposal to STAR voting. Given the assessment I was able to provide, I see no reason why this procedure would behave badly. It converts STAR ballots to scores of 0 or 1 in a way similar to how 3-2-1 ballots are converted, and while it can’t guarantee the STAR result within the states that use it, it can only fail to give the STAR result when another candidate is rated higher than the two finalists on over half the ballots, an event which should be rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It also works with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Borda_count&quot;&gt;borda count&lt;/a&gt;, but because borda is (at least arguably) worse than plurality, I have chosen to omit it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Since Quinn was applying the criteria to the tally procedure for 3-2-1 voting, this originally said “the 3-2-1 winner”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It’s probably more accurate to say that STAR awards 0 points to both finalists for ballots where they are tied, but saying it awards 1 point to both like my procedure does will never change the outcome, so I ignore this for simplicity. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Should you pursue common or rare achievements?</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/07/21/should-you-pursue-common-or-rare-achievements"/>
			<updated>2018-07-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/07/21/should-you-pursue-common-or-rare-achievements</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve been considering what video game achievements are most worth aiming for. Specifically, the question is whether I should go after common achievements or rare achievements. I’d been targeting rare achievements, but it occurred to me that I might be better off going after common ones instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason to pursue common achievements is that they’re generally lower-hanging fruit. All else equal, the easier an achievement is, the more people will have it. Thus, if you simply want to maximize the number of achievements you have, going after more common achievements seems like the way to go. Occasionally a rare achievement may seem just as easy, but that shouldn’t be your main focus, only a possibility that you pursue as it comes up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor to consider is the potential embarrassment of not having a particular achievement. Lacking a common achievement could be very embarrassing. After all, if an achievement is held by 80% of the player base, then how come you don’t have it? On the other hand, lacking a rare achievement is much more understandable. Unless you’re a huge achievement hunter, no one will be surprised that you’re missing an achievement that less than 1% of all players have. Being embarrassed over not having an achievement does seem like a rather unlikely scenario, but it’s always possible that a friend may want to compare achievements or something, so it is a factor worth considering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While common achievements may be better when someone is looking through all your achievements, rare achievements are nice when you can direct attention to a specific set of achievements. Steam is a major video game platform that allows you to do just that, offering both a general achievement showcase option and a rarest achievement showcase option for player profiles. Rare achievements will generally be more impressive than common ones, so if you’re looking to show off what you’ve achieved, focusing on rare achievements seems like the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re unconcerned with what others think, you may still want to target rare achievements because of the satisfaction you feel upon achieving them. This will obviously vary from person to person, but it’s likely that common achievements don’t feel as special to complete since so many other people have already acquired them. It’s generally much more satisfying to accomplish something that few others have. Therefore, if others’ opinions of your completed achievements don’t bother you but you do care about the satisfaction of obtaining rare achievements, focusing on those rare achievements appears to be a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After considering these arguments, I decided that going after rare achievements was still the best decision for me. I don’t think I care about quantity too much, and I don’t expect to be embarrassed about missing common achievements. In contrast, I can choose to show off the rare achievements I have, and acquiring them is a rewarding activity for me. While I don’t expect this to be the best option for everyone, I am reasonably confident that I have made the right decision.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Why discuss superintelligence?</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/07/01/why-discuss-superintelligence"/>
			<updated>2018-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/07/01/why-discuss-superintelligence</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My site now contains a miscellaneous section with exactly one page, the &lt;a href=&quot;/miscellaneous/superintelligence-reference-page&quot;&gt;Superintelligence reference page&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/03/02/how-intelligent-are-we&quot;&gt;briefly brought up superintelligence&lt;/a&gt; in the past, but I’ve never discussed it in detail. However, given that others have already written so much about it, I feel like it makes more sense to collect the resources I think do a good job of explaining it. Therefore, if you have no idea what superintelligence is or why you should care about it, I’d recommend starting with some of the links in the &lt;a href=&quot;/miscellaneous/superintelligence-reference-page#introductions&quot;&gt;Introductions section&lt;/a&gt; before reading on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You back? Good. At this point, you might be wondering why I’ve singled out this topic as one worth prioritizing. The answer to that question is that superintelligence is an existential risk. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.existential-risk.org/concept.pdf&quot;&gt;Using a conservative estimate&lt;/a&gt;, it is possible for humanity to create 10&lt;sup&gt;34&lt;/sup&gt; fulfilling years of human life throughout the remainder of the universe’s existence. Thus, ensuring humanity remains capable of doing so is extremely important. This and other concerns &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.existential-risk.org/concept.pdf&quot;&gt;justify treating existential risk prevention as a global priority&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because superintelligence is an existential risk, ensuring that it is &lt;a href=&quot;/miscellaneous/superintelligence-reference-page#alignment-problem&quot;&gt;aligned with human values&lt;/a&gt; is a very important problem. Some organizations even consider it to potentially be &lt;a href=&quot;https://80000hours.org/articles/cause-selection/&quot;&gt;the most important global problem&lt;/a&gt; that humanity has identified thus far. At the same time, media coverage of this issue and AI in general has been increasing, and a lot of it is not very good. Therefore, it seems important to have resources available on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of this post, the reference page has only three sections, but I plan to expand upon it in the future. Topics that I plan to add include the orthogonality and instrumental convergence theses, the intelligence explosion concept, and scenarios without an intelligence explosion. There’s a lot of room to grow the page, and I think doing so is definitely worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>My thoughts on Microsoft acquiring GitHub</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/06/04/my-thoughts-on-microsoft-acquiring-github"/>
			<updated>2018-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/06/04/my-thoughts-on-microsoft-acquiring-github</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today it was announced that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2018/6/4/17422788/microsoft-github-acquisition-official-deal&quot;&gt;Microsoft is acquiring GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. The responses to this event have been mixed, with some people expressing optimism and others fear. I have two lines of thought regarding this subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I don’t expect Microsoft to ruin GitHub. I agree with those who believe that &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to/resir014/the-microsoft-thing-cb&quot;&gt;Microsoft genuinely cares&lt;/a&gt; about open source. So long as software is a complement to Microsoft’s products, Microsoft is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/Complement&quot;&gt;incentivized to support open source software&lt;/a&gt;. I was worried when I discovered that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geekwire.com/2016/this-is-the-new-microsoft-windows-slips-to-no-3-as-company-shifts-to-the-cloud/&quot;&gt;Microsoft’s revenue from Windows is dropping&lt;/a&gt; since operating systems are an obvious complement of software, but luckily Microsoft seems to be pivoting to cloud services, another complement of software. Therefore, I expect that Microsoft will at least avoid damaging GitHub in any way since it stands to gain from open source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does worry me is the larger pattern that this acquisition is a part of. Microsoft has made &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_mergers_and_acquisitions_by_Microsoft#Key_acquisitions&quot;&gt;a lot of acquisitions&lt;/a&gt; in the past, and it’s far from the only company to do so. This pattern, along with some other factors, has resulted in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://srconstantin.wordpress.com/2018/05/31/monopoly-a-manifesto-and-fact-post/&quot;&gt;major increase in market power&lt;/a&gt;, which means there’s a lot less competition among companies. This leads to a variety of problems, including &lt;a href=&quot;http://rooseveltinstitute.org/how-widespread-labor-monopsony-some-new-results-suggest-its-pervasive/&quot;&gt;lower wages&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2017-09-01/america-s-superstar-companies-are-a-drag-on-growth&quot;&gt;less economic growth&lt;/a&gt;, and the phenomenon known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/02/09/considerations-on-cost-disease/&quot;&gt;cost disease&lt;/a&gt;, among many others. So while I don’t think there’s anything wrong with this acquisition specifically, in context it is part of an extremely harmful pattern that needs to be ended.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Outlining the opposite of a singleton</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/06/01/outlining-the-opposite-of-a-singleton"/>
			<updated>2018-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/06/01/outlining-the-opposite-of-a-singleton</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/02/09/singletons-and-universal-inevitable-threats&quot;&gt;one of my previous posts&lt;/a&gt;, I discussed the concept of a singleton as defined by Nick Bostrom. Now I’d like to consider what the rough opposite of a singleton would look like, based on what has been written by others on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the obvious place to start is Scott Alexander’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/07/30/meditations-on-moloch/&quot;&gt;Meditations On Moloch&lt;/a&gt;. In it, Moloch is introduced as that which causes the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In some competition optimizing for X, the opportunity arises to throw some other value under the bus for improved X. Those who take it prosper. Those who don’t take it die out. Eventually, everyone’s relative status is about the same as before, but everyone’s absolute status is worse than before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of situation is known as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://conceptually.org/concepts/coordination-problems/&quot;&gt;coordination problem&lt;/a&gt;, something I discussed previously in the context of &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/01/26/video-game-boycotts&quot;&gt;boycotting video games&lt;/a&gt;. If those in the competition could choose to cooperate, they could easily coordinate to avoid sacrificing any other values. But as long as they are competing, once one of them chooses to sacrifice something for a short-term advantage, the rest must do the same or be eliminated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that in less intense competitions with fewer participants, there’s a greater chance that no one will take the first step, allowing values that could be traded away to remain. Total coordination failure would involve a large number of entities competing, enough that any opportunity to trade away a value is taken almost immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As enlightening as I find this post to be, it does not identify the opposite of a singleton. Moloch is the force that might lead to this opposite manifesting, but it is not the opposite itself. In order to find that, we will have to look elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where should we look? Well, we know that if the opposite ever manifests, it will be because of Moloch. Thus, a “competition optimizing for X” will be involved. But what X are we looking for? It needs to be something fundamental, something that isn’t destroyed even if civilization is eliminated and the world is nothing but chaos. And what is more fundamental for agents in a competition than existence itself? It’s not like you can even participate in a competition if you don’t exist in the first place. The answer, it would seem, is survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not quite that simple. Take evolution, for example. Survival is actually not its most important component; reproduction is. Now if one holds reproduction as their terminal goal, survival does happen to be a key instrumental goal. However, it is safe to say that evolution is a competition optimizing for reproduction. After all, if evolution were a competition optimizing for survival, then it would be weird to find that most species could die of old age. In contrast, all species are capable of reproducing, so reproduction fits the bill much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads us to our next major source, &lt;a href=&quot;https://qualiacomputing.com/2016/08/20/wireheading_done_right/&quot;&gt;Wireheading Done Right: Stay Positive Without Going Insane&lt;/a&gt;. Most of this post is actually not relevant to our discussion, but this paragraph is an exception:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I will define a &lt;em&gt;pure replicator&lt;/em&gt;, in the context of agents and minds, to be an intelligence that is indifferent towards the valence of its conscious states and those of others. A pure replicator invests all of its energy and resources into surviving and reproducing, even at the cost of continuous suffering to themselves or others. Its main evolutionary advantage is that it does not need to spend any resources making the world a better place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The given definition, while useful in its original context, is oddly focused on what a pure replicator doesn’t do. The sentence that follows is much more important to us. A pure replicator focuses solely on surviving and reproducing. Keeping in mind that survival is merely an instrumental goal, I will redefine a pure replicator as an agent that optimizes for its own reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have this concept, we can finally get around to naming and defining the opposite of a singleton. I have chosen to name this concept a &lt;em&gt;replicator world&lt;/em&gt;. I define a replicator world as a world order in which all highest-level agencies are pure replicators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s break this new definition down. First of all, a replicator world is a world order just as a singleton is. Both are incompatible with all other world orders, as world orders extend throughout their domain and do not leave room for anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we need to know what a highest-level agency is. Agencies are able to combine with each other to form a new agency, which is considered to be one level higher than the agencies forming it. For example, cells can be thought of as agencies that come together to form higher-level agencies called multicellular organisms. A highest-level agency is an agency that is not part of any higher-level agency. In the case of a singleton, the singleton itself is the only highest-level agency, and all other agencies are a part of it. In the case of a replicator world, there are many different highest-level agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, all those highest-level agencies have to be pure replicators. It’s important that this condition be restricted to agencies at the highest level because pure replicators are bad at forming higher-level agencies thanks to the free-rider problem. When agencies form a higher-level agency, they do so because they expect to benefit from it. However, if an individual agency chooses not to contribute to the effort, it will still receive the vast majority of the benefits from the higher-level agency despite experiencing a much lower cost. There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2016/02/11/minimum-viable-superorganism/&quot;&gt;solutions to this problem&lt;/a&gt;, but they tend to involve other values that a pure replicator will immediately trade away for an increased ability to reproduce. Thus, highest-level agencies that are pure replicators will likely consist of agencies that aren’t pure replicators. For example, an organism that functions as a pure replicator may be composed of non-cancerous cells that do not function as pure replicators. This justifies restricting the condition of being a pure replicator to highest-level agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One feature of replicator worlds is that, shortly after their creation, they will always be roughly at their &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carrying_capacity&quot;&gt;carrying capacity&lt;/a&gt;. This occurs because agencies optimizing for reproduction will initially use up excess resources at an exponential rate as their population grows. While the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.khanacademy.org/science/biology/ecology/population-growth-and-regulation/a/exponential-logistic-growth&quot;&gt;logistic model&lt;/a&gt; suggests that growth will slow down again as the population approaches the carrying capacity, by the time growth has been substantially slowed the population will already be roughly at the carrying capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This in turn implies that agencies in replicator worlds will have access to almost no resources beyond those necessary for survival, as carrying capacity is the population size in which all resources are used simply for survival. While it is almost certain that replicator worlds will expand to gain access to additional resources, any time pure replicators come upon excess resources they will immediately begin reproducing until there are enough offspring that all resources are used solely for survival, restoring the population to carrying capacity. This will likely occur fast enough that no agency will have access to a significant amount of excess resources at any point in their existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this, it can be deduced that replicator worlds experience little to no technological development. All agencies have to choose between exploration and exploitation, a dilemma known as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://conceptually.org/concepts/explore-or-exploit/&quot;&gt;explore-exploit tradeoff&lt;/a&gt;. However, agencies in replicator worlds are strongly incentivized to exploit any resources they have rather than use them for exploration. Most of the time they will only be able to survive if they exploit all their resources to that end. Even at times when they have excess resources, however, pure replicators will want to use them for reproduction. While exploration could yield results that help a pure replicator by, for example, increasing how efficiently it can use resources, this sort of discovery takes time, time an agency in a replicator world will likely not have. Other agencies are seeking out resources as well, and once the excess resources are gone the easiest resources to obtain may be the ones being used for exploration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If exploration is this unrewarding, agencies will likely sacrifice the ability to explore at all. If doing so gives agencies even a slight advantage in resource usage, this move could very well make sense in such an intensive competition. Interestingly, such a modification would be the last one an agency makes, as modifications are inherently a form of exploration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another feature of replicator worlds is a lack of coordination at the highest level. This should be expected, as a singleton has everything coordinated by one agency. Several major implications result from this. One is that no governments or other organizations comprised of highest-level agencies will exist. Organizations are dependent on coordination between their members, but this will not be possible in a replicator world. In fact, since an organization would actually count as a higher-level agency, it is by definition impossible for an organization to be formed from highest-level agencies. Thus, there are only two possible ways that something like a government could exist in a replicator world: either it must be a pure replicator, or it must be a lower-level agency within a pure replicator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another implication is the lack of an economy or any looser means of coordination among highest-level agencies. While these forms of coordination may not be tight enough to form higher-level agencies and therefore do not suffer from a definition issue, they are nonetheless dependent on a process that cannot happen between pure replicators. As such, they can only possibly appear in a replicator world if they can exist within a pure replicator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that this outline of a replicator world effectively captures what I would intuitively expect the opposite of a singleton to look like. However, this by no means implies that it is correct. I expect to at the very least significantly alter my conception of this concept as I think about it more. However, I am quite happy with this as a first attempt to tackle understanding this area.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Freedom of speech is good</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/05/20/freedom-of-speech-is-good"/>
			<updated>2018-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/05/20/freedom-of-speech-is-good</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/04/28/freedom-of-speech-is-bad&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I laid out what I consider to be the strongest argument against freedom of speech. Now I will cover what I believe to be the flaw in that argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that argument’s analogy, ideological propaganda produced by think tanks is equated with pathogens produced by bioweapon labs. But this comparison misses something. Multiple pathogens will all weaken a host more than just one of them would, but multiple ideologies will contradict and weaken each other, influencing people less. This gives freedom of speech an advantage that “freedom to distribute pathogens” lacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When freedom of speech is eliminated, it is generally done so by one group that chooses to allow its own speech but bans that of other groups it opposes. Thus, one set of think tanks continues to distribute their ideology, but the others are no longer able to do so. This allows the favored ideology to have a greater impact on people than the spread of all ideologies would’ve. If one bioweapon lab banned all the others from distributing their pathogens, it would be an improvement; this does not hold true for think tanks and ideologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t imply that freedom of speech and the marketplace of ideas automatically lead to the truth, but it does suggest that they are components of a system that does. Without freedom of speech, it’s much easier to entrench false ideas within society. Creating a marketplace of ideas at least puts some pressure on ideas to be truthful. However, some additional mechanism is necessary to ensure that more truthful ideas are believed and spread more. Otherwise, the marketplace of ideas, which directly optimizes for ideas that are believed and spread, ceases to indirectly optimize for truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know what such a mechanism would look like, but developing one seems like it could become more important as the power of propaganda increases. In the meantime, defending freedom of speech ought to help. It won’t solve the problem, but at the very least it should slow down the rate at which the situation deteriorates.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Freedom of speech is bad</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/04/28/freedom-of-speech-is-bad"/>
			<updated>2018-04-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/04/28/freedom-of-speech-is-bad</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I consider freedom of speech to be one of the most important foundations of today’s society. However, in this post I’d like to present what I believe is the strongest argument against free speech, then follow it up with the reason I think said argument is wrong in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The groundwork for this argument (though certainly not the argument itself) is laid out in detail in Scott Alexander’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/07/30/meditations-on-moloch/&quot;&gt;Meditations On Moloch&lt;/a&gt;, which I recommend you read first. The most relevant part is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The point is – imagine a country full of bioweapon labs, where people toil day and night to invent new infectious agents. The existence of these labs, and their right to throw whatever they develop in the water supply is protected by law. And the country is also linked by the world’s most perfect mass transit system that every single person uses every day, so that any new pathogen can spread to the entire country instantaneously. You’d expect things to start going bad for that city pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Well, we have about a zillion think tanks researching new and better forms of propaganda. And we have constitutionally protected freedom of speech. And we have the Internet. So we’re kind of screwed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The obvious way to solve the problem in the analogy is to remove the right to exist and contaminate the water supply that the bioweapon labs currently possess. The other apparent option, eliminating the mass transit system, is both less effective, since the pathogens will merely spread at a lower rate, and more costly, since the mass transit system is otherwise a very useful innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implications of this are troubling. The problems with eliminating the mass transit system appear analogous to problems with eliminating the Internet. Eliminating freedom of speech also seems like it would be more effective, so the only part of the analogy that remains to be upheld is the lower cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the point where the marketplace of ideas will be brought up to justify keeping freedom of speech. Allowing ideas to compete so that the truth may come out on top makes freedom of speech very beneficial, and thus much more costly to remove than the analogous rights of the bioweapon labs. Unfortunately, another point made by Scott Alexander suggests that this is a weak argument:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Memes optimize for making people want to accept them and pass them on – so like capitalism and democracy, they’re optimizing for a  &lt;em&gt;proxy&lt;/em&gt;  of making us happy, but that proxy can easily get uncoupled from the original goal.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Chain letters, urban legends, propaganda, and viral marketing are all examples of memes that don’t satisfy our explicit values (true and useful) but are sufficiently memetically virulent that they spread anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the marketplace of ideas is not actually as valuable as it may seem. After all, think tanks wouldn’t be that large of a threat if it were; their ideas would simply be outcompeted by the truth. This implies that the cost of eliminating free speech is not that high, and thus that doing so is the correct solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next post will be an explanation of where I think this argument breaks down.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Comic Sans is a great font</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/04/01/comic-sans-is-a-great-font"/>
			<updated>2018-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/04/01/comic-sans-is-a-great-font</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Everyone loves to hate on Comic Sans. Even those who know nothing about typography will spend the time to go on long rants about how awful it is. But the truth of the matter is entirely different from what common knowledge suggests. In reality, Comic Sans is a great font.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes Comic Sans so great? For one thing, it’s an easily recognizable font. It was originally released as one of five fonts supplied by Windows 95. This allowed it to spread very quickly as many personal computer users employed it in their printouts. The intense hatred that many hold for it only renders it even more recognizable. For them, Comic Sans is the enemy, and an inability to identify your enemy leads to a swift defeat. Thus, the Comic Sans haters cannot help but fuel its recognizability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comic Sans is also often preferred by those with dyslexia. While it is not a specialized font and therefore does not perfectly fulfill this role, it does a much better job than practically any font the Comic Sans haters will hold up. Very few fonts can match the legibility and letter spacing that Comic Sans brings to the table. It does contain mirrored letters which allow specialized fonts to surpass it, but giving those up trades away consistency, which can be very distracting for other readers. Comic Sans does an excellent job of balancing other concerns with accessibility for dyslexic readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One common complaint against Comic Sans is that it is an informal font often used in formal contexts. As long as the uninformed make use of it in documents in which the informal tone it sets is inappropriate, its very existence is detrimental, or so the argument goes. However, this fails to take into account the concept of &lt;a href=&quot;https://conceptually.org/concepts/signalling-and-countersignalling/&quot;&gt;countersignaling&lt;/a&gt;. Countersignaling is when you communicate that you strongly possess a property by not making it more conspicuous. For example, those who are newly rich will likely flaunt their wealth to make it clear that they are no longer part of the middle class, but those who are already known to be rich will worry about differentiating themselves from the newly rich, and will accomplish this by &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; flaunting their wealth. This only works because they are not afraid of being mistaken for a member of the lower or middle classes. That’s the reason countersignaling even works: you must be so confident in the trait you are countersignaling that you are willing to avoid emphasizing it because you know others will pick up on it anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of Comic Sans, many formal documents are very obviously formal regardless of the font. For instance, a doctor’s diagnosis is unlikely to be mistaken for something informal, and thus it is possible to get away with countersignaling. In fact, in basically every case in which you can tell that an informal tone is inappropriate, countersignaling is a viable strategy. So if you really want to emphasize your formality in such an instance, don’t use some standard formal font. Use Comic Sans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if Comic Sans is such as great font, why does everyone seem to hate it? The answer to that question lies in the history of graphic design and the rise of the internet. Early personal computers dramatically reduced the cost of high quality print design, and colleges began to produce a much larger number of graphic design graduates. However, personal computers also put the power of graphic design into the hands of everyone who owned them. While most people were slower to figure out they had this power than the graphic design students were, they did eventually learn. This was only the first step in the reduction of graphic designers’ power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second, far more dramatic step was the growth of web design. As print design began to die off, designers had to learn to code just to retain relevance. This made them understandably bitter, and they took their anger out on those performing graphic design without a degree. And what font did these amateurs with personal computers happen to be using? That’s right: Comic Sans. This made the font an obvious means of defining &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ingroups_and_outgroups&quot;&gt;an ingroup and an outgroup&lt;/a&gt;. If you liked Comic Sans and used it a lot, you were a useless pretender who lacked even the most basic design knowledge. But if you hated Comic Sans, then you were a sensible designer who understood how things actually worked. Thus, hating Comic Sans was associated with understanding graphic design, and anyone who wanted to not look like an idiot learned to avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I say enough is enough. It’s time to take Comic Sans back from the elitist graphic designers who use it as a symbol of their superiority. If you have a website, switch it over to Comic Sans. If you design documents, start writing them in Comic Sans. In every situation in which you get to choose the font, choose Comic Sans. Together we can retake this wonderful font from those who have abused it for so long!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>How to win The Game</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/03/14/how-to-win-the-game"/>
			<updated>2018-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/03/14/how-to-win-the-game</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For anyone who has no idea what the title is referring to, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Game_(mind_game)&quot;&gt;The Game&lt;/a&gt; is a mental game with three simple rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You are playing The Game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every time you think about The Game, you lose.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Loss of The Game must be announced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These rules lead to a meme that propagates itself without generally providing value to the minds it inhabits. Everyone is either not thinking about The Game, in which case it has no effect on them, or thinking about The Game, in which case they are losing it. However, it is possible for some people to get utility out of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By spreading this meme to other minds, those that enjoy watching others lose can benefit from what is otherwise a detrimental meme. However, this is a negative-sum game, so it is still harmful to the group as a whole. This means that while it is possible for a few trolls to benefit, it would still be best if The Game didn’t exist. Unfortunately, it is intentionally designed such that it cannot be ended. Winning is simply impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that means is we need to get a little creative. If something you want to accomplish is impossible, your next goal should be to try to merely approximate that thing. For example, literally defying gravity is, to the best of our knowledge, impossible. There is no way to just ignore it. However, this does not prevent airplanes and rockets from working. While they do not literally defy gravity, they do a good job of approximating what defying gravity would look like. Likewise, we want to approximate how winning The Game would appear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to do so, we first need to establish what that approximation is like. Our goal is to end a negative-sum game. Thus, an important property we’re looking for is that The Game no longer reduces total utility. If we can accomplish this, then we will have approximated winning The Game well enough for our purposes. The problem is that we cannot just modify The Game to have the desired properties. This means our only option is to create something new. If we want to prevent total utility from being reduced, we’ll have to increase total utility, which will require the creation of a positive-sum game. Furthermore, this positive-sum game should provide utility whenever The Game reduces it so as to better approximate The Game’s nonexistence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now present my solution to this task: The Meta-Game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You are playing The Meta-Game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every time you think about The Game, you win The Meta-Game.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Winning The Meta-Game must be announced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first rule ensures that The Meta-Game applies to everyone The Game applies to. The second rule directly combats the negative-sum nature of The Game by making The Meta-Game a positive-sum game that awards players on the exact condition that causes them to lose The Game. The third rule helps The Meta-Game spread in the same way The Game spreads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might notice a problem here. Sure, players win The Meta-Game at the same time they lose The Game, but does the win really cancel out the loss? After all, doesn’t the utility gained or lost depend on how much you actually care about The Game vs. The Meta-Game and winning vs. losing? While this could be a problem in some cases, I think it can be reduced to a nonissue for most people. Remember that The Game is usually brought up by those who enjoy making others lose it. Most people will probably enjoy foiling the trolls’ plans quite a bit, so they should at least break even on utility, if not gain some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even this reasoning is not quite perfect, though, as it is actually circular. You have to defeat the troll in order to gain the utility that allows you to defeat the troll. This can be solved by having the troll be gradually defeated over multiple wins. Initially, they are only defeated a little bit thanks to the utility gained simply by winning a game. The next time The Game is lost, utility is gained both from winning a game and from knowing that the troll will be partially defeated, as they were last time. The third time, even more utility is gained thanks to the increased success at defeating the troll the previous time. This process continues indefinitely, and the utility gained from every time The Meta-Game is won will converge to the amount we previously arrived at circularly. (It is reasonable to assume convergence here since divergence would imply that winning The Meta-Game enough times would allow an arbitrarily large amount of utility to be gained upon every further win.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you followed all that and agreed with it, then congratulations, because you have just won The Game and therefore become invulnerable to it. Please be sure to use your newfound powers responsibly and spread The Meta-Game anywhere The Game has taken root. If you didn’t follow that or you disagree with my reasoning, I welcome you to leave a comment asking questions or arguing against this.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Arguing over definitions</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/03/08/arguing-over-definitions"/>
			<updated>2018-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/03/08/arguing-over-definitions</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently got into an argument involving topics like whether water was wet and whether hotdogs were sandwiches. What all the topics had in common was that they were not arguments over facts but rather arguments over definitions. This means there is nothing in observable reality that can be pointed to in order to resolve them. What’s worse is that many arguments will fall into this category by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that until all relevant definitions are agreed upon, an argument will often not be about facts. As long as one definition isn’t agreed upon, the participants can make two different statements using the same exact words, which is terrible for communication. If “a hotdog is a sandwich” is interpreted by one person as “a hotdog is meat on bread” and by another person as “a hotdog is meat between two pieces of bread”, they may both think the other person is crazy. If they realize that the dispute is really over definitions, they may still believe that it is unreasonable to use any definition besides the one they use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there a way to resolve this type of dispute? I would argue that it makes the most sense to debate how practical the definitions are. This includes how observable they are and how useful they are. For example, it’s pretty simple to observe if a hotdog has meat on bread. However, it may be a little harder to tell how many pieces of bread there are, such as when the bun is either split in two or almost split in two. These states are similar enough that observing the difference can take extra effort, penalizing definitions that distinguish between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what matters more than how difficult the required observations are is how useful those observations are. If distinguishing between one piece of bread and two pieces of bread is important, then it hardly matters if doing so takes a little more effort. However, barring something like cultural significance, this distinction does not seem useful, so the observation difficulty wins out (at least in my opinion). On the other hand, if someone attempted to define the word dignity as a category consisting of rocks, rockets, and cats, their definition would probably be judged as inferior to the standard definition. While it is easier to observe those things than it is to observe an abstract concept like dignity, the standard definition is simply much more useful and thus wins out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with this approach to resolving definition arguments is that it merely attempts to transform them into factual arguments. If the definitions relevant to determining which definition is more practical are also not agreed upon, you end up with a case of infinite recursion. At the end of the day, language is a fundamentally imprecise tool for communication. It’s very useful and works quite well, but it’s not perfect. As of now, though, it’s the best thing we’ve got.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>How intelligent are we?</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/03/02/how-intelligent-are-we"/>
			<updated>2018-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/03/02/how-intelligent-are-we</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Humans are generally thought of as the most intelligent beings to exist, as we have discovered nothing that appears to be more intelligent than us. But how intelligent are we compared to the theoretically attainable maximum? I believe that we are far less intelligent than is physically possible. This is because we possess roughly the minimum level of intelligence necessary to create a technological civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand why this is so, we must look at how we came to have this level of intelligence in the first place. Over a period of about 50 million years, the brains of rat-like creatures evolved into the brains of chimps. This was a complex process that involved major structural changes. However, going from chimp brains to human brains only took about 5 million years and required only minor changes to brain structure, suggesting a faster but more gradual process that was unlikely to end at the exact time civilization started. So if one were to ask the question of why we &lt;em&gt;stopped&lt;/em&gt; at our current level of intelligence, I would argue that we haven’t necessarily. Instead, we’re at this level because it allowed us to begin building civilization, a process that occurs on a much faster timescale than evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agricultural Revolution occurred roughly 12,000 years ago. Since then, humanity has done all sorts of crazy things involved in building civilization, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://lukemuehlhauser.com/there-was-only-one-industrial-revolution/&quot;&gt;at least one&lt;/a&gt; other major technological revolution, while evolution has only had time to make the most minor of changes. Thus, while there may still be room for evolutionary pressures to improve primate intelligence in the same way it’s been improving for the past 5 million years, the 12,000 years over which civilization has existed are simply too small for noticeable progress to occur. If a lower level of intelligence enabled the creation of civilization, then it would’ve moved too fast for us to be able to observe it in its current state with our current level of intelligence. Thus, whatever level of intelligence we observe ourselves to have from within a civilization is roughly the minimum level of intelligence capable of giving rise to that civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This in turn suggests that there could be much more room for our intelligence to grow. It seems unlikely that the minimum level of intelligence that enables civilization would also be the maximum level of intelligence enabled by the laws of physics. Thus, I propose that humans are likely well below the theoretical maximum intelligence level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether we are close to maximum intelligence is important for several topics. Brain-machine interfaces are much more important if there is significant room for them to augment our intelligence. Superintelligence is a greater concern the further we are from maximum intelligence. A distant maximum intelligence also leaves room for technologies like genetic engineering to possibly enhance human intelligence in the near-term. If these are all possible, then we would be wise to prepare for them ahead of time.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Singletons and universal inevitable threats</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/02/09/singletons-and-universal-inevitable-threats"/>
			<updated>2018-02-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/02/09/singletons-and-universal-inevitable-threats</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One concept I find particularly fascinating is that of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://nickbostrom.com/fut/singleton.html&quot;&gt;singleton&lt;/a&gt;. As defined by Nick Bostrom, a singleton is “a world order in which there is a single decision-making agency at the highest level”. He states that such an agency would have “the ability to prevent any threats (internal or external) to its own existence and supremacy”. However, it is not at all obvious to me that this is true. To crystallize my intuition I would like to introduce my own concept: the universal inevitable threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An inevitable threat is defined as a threat that eliminates an agency regardless of the actions that agency takes. This leaves open the possibility of delaying the threat for a finite period of time, but beyond that, the agency may only choose how to spend the time it has prior to the threat’s realization. It can neither eliminate the threat nor hold it off indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A universal inevitable threat is then defined as an inevitable threat that applies to all possible agencies. A notable property of such a threat is that it cannot be brought about by an agency, as this would imply that the agency had a course of action that would result in the threat not occurring and therefore that the threat was not inevitable relative to that agency. This concept is relevant because if a universal inevitable threat exists, then no agency is able to prevent all threats to itself, including a singleton. Furthermore, several plausible candidates for a universal inevitable threat can be identified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first possibility is simply &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ultimate_fate_of_the_universe&quot;&gt;the end of the universe&lt;/a&gt;. Exactly how the universe will end has yet to be determined, but most hypotheses posit scenarios that appear to be universal inevitable threats. One example is the heat death of the universe, which would result in a state of maximum entropy in which no information processing can take place. Since information processing seems to be essential for agencies to operate, this scenario would count as a universal inevitable threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another potential end of the universe is the Big Rip scenario. In this case, the universe’s increasing expansion rips everything apart into elementary particles and radiation. Unless an agency can somehow develop a way to survive the infinite expansion rate that is eventually reached, all agencies are eliminated, making this a universal inevitable threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Big Crunch is yet another possible end state of the universe. This possibility involves the universe collapsing into a dimensionless singularity. A related scenario is the Big Bounce, which follows the Big Crunch with another Big Bang to create a cycle. Unless some agency can survive a singularity of infinite density, both cases are universal inevitable threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another category of universal inevitable threat candidates is resource depletion scenarios. Some scenarios for the end of the universe can actually be framed as falling under this category. For example, heat death can be viewed as the universe running out of negentropy. However, it is possible that some other resource is both essential for agencies to function and depleted prior to the end of the universe. The depletion of such a resource would be a universal inevitable threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final category of candidates for universal inevitable threats is that of naturally occurring physics disasters. An example of this would be false vacuum decay. If the universe is currently part of a metastable vacuum, it could be disrupted, creating a bubble of lower-energy vacuum that expands at the speed of light. This could fundamentally alter the universe in such a way as to destroy any agencies in existence prior to the event. 
False vacuum decay and any similar physics disasters that occur naturally would likely be universal inevitable threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it is not yet possible to confirm the existence of a universal inevitable threat, there does seem to be a significant probability of one existing. In particular, the end of the universe is very likely to be one. If one exists, it would prove that no agency is able to prevent all threats to itself, and thus that singletons do not possess this power, as seems probable to me.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Colonizing Mars does not mean abandoning Earth</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/02/04/colonizing-mars-does-not-mean-abandoning-earth"/>
			<updated>2018-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/02/04/colonizing-mars-does-not-mean-abandoning-earth</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Colonizing Mars is often talked about in the context of preventing the extinction of humanity. This has led to the unfortunate misconception that colonization results in the abandonment of Earth. I’d like to take the time to explain why this doesn’t happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we explore just why Earth wouldn’t be abandoned, it will be useful to review the extinction risk argument for colonizing another planet. The argument starts by noting that out of all species to ever live on Earth, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/evolution/extinction/massext/index.html&quot;&gt;99.9% have gone extinct&lt;/a&gt;. It then goes on to point out how most of these extinctions occurred in planet-wide events called mass extinctions. Thus, establishing a species on another planet would be a good way to increase its chances of survival. If a cataclysmic event wipes the species off one planet, it is simply a matter of waiting for the dust to settle before reintroducing them from the other planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One detail of this plan is extremely important: so long as no such event has occurred, it is essential that the species be well-established on &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; planets. Once the species is wiped off one planet, it becomes as vulnerable as it used to be until its presence on that planet is restored. Abandoning the species’ home planet in favor of a newly colonized one thus completely fails to increase the species’ survival rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The misconception stems from the idea that once Mars is colonized, Earth will become unnecessary to the survival of the human race. Since the end of humanity on Earth no longer means the end of humanity, we are free to abandon it whenever we want. But this ignores that the whole purpose of colonizing Mars was to have two planets instead of one. Mars may be essential to the plan, but so is Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But won’t having Mars as a backup mean we put less effort and resources toward preventing a catastrophe on Earth? No, because there will still be plenty of people living on Earth, and their lives will be as valuable as ever. Humanity will be wiped off the face of the Earth only if no way exists to prevent it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if Mars is colonized, then Earth can actually be re-inhabited, given enough time. Therefore, colonizing Mars is actually the opposite of abandoning Earth; it is a means by which to remain on Earth. That is why many people see it not as the abandonment of our home, but as an important step to take for protecting both it and humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Can boycotts be solved?</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/02/01/can-boycotts-be-solved"/>
			<updated>2018-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/02/01/can-boycotts-be-solved</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/01/26/video-game-boycotts&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about why individuals’ incentives will prevent video game boycotts from succeeding. Now I’d like to discuss potential solutions (or at least vague outlines for potential solutions) to this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first idea that comes to mind is looking at historical successes. Two successful boycotts that I’m aware of are the Continental Association and the Montgomery bus boycott. For those who don’t know, the Continental Association was a boycott of British goods by the American colonies prior to the American Revolutionary War, and the Montgomery bus boycott was a protest against the segregated bus system in Montgomery, Alabama during the American Civil Rights Movement. In looking at these examples, I hope to identify both parts of a coordination mechanism: an agreement and an enforcement mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Continental Association’s agreement is easy to find. The Association’s articles stated that colonists would refuse to import British goods and American merchants would avoid price gouging to ease the resulting burden. Likewise, the articles provide several enforcement mechanisms. Those violating the agreement were to be publicly ostracized and condemned. Committees of inspection were set up to monitor businesses. Colonies had to cease all dealings with any colony that did not comply. Additionally, violence was employed to force compliance on some occasions. These mechanisms were successful enough for all but one colony to comply up until the war began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Montgomery bus boycott also has a simple agreement. The buses would not be ridden until the city agreed to switch to a compromise between the current rules and desegregation. The enforcement mechanism is less obvious, but given the strength of the black community and its churches, it’s reasonable to assume it was social pressure. Community members often helped each other out, and losing that support could be devastating, so if the community said you should join the boycott, you probably joined the boycott. Similarly to before, this was enough for the boycott to last until the United States Supreme Court ruled segregation on public transportation illegal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to video game boycotts, the agreement seems easy to create. Refuse to purchase the game until the game’s publisher stops whatever prompted the boycott. The difficult part is the enforcement mechanism. The Continental Association’s methods don’t seem particularly helpful. Committees of inspection could be ignored, no obvious analog to colonies exists, and violence is a poor solution for most problems. That leaves social mechanisms, the strategy that was also employed for the Montgomery bus boycott. This is probably the most plausible option, but it’s still pretty bad. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.learning-theories.com/online-disinhibition-effect-suler.html&quot;&gt;online disinhibition effect&lt;/a&gt; weakens social restrictions, reducing the chances that an online community will be able to pressure its members into coordination. Therefore, I think it would be wiser to look at other options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most powerful coordination mechanism ever created by civilization is probably government. In a government with legislative and executive branches, the legislative branch sets the agreements while the executive branch enforces them. Thus, one way to solve our problem is to get a law passed that bans the targeted activity. Then everyone is forced to “boycott” offending games by means of their nonexistence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this idea is not without its problems. First of all, you need to grab the attention of your legislators while thousands of other causes also vie for their attention. Next, you need to convince them that supporting your law is in their best interests, even though there will almost certainly be objections and proposals for changes that no one will agree on. Additionally, you need to actually have a law for them to support. If you can’t specify the activity that needs banned well enough, your law will either be ineffective or ban actions that should be allowed. This brings up another problem, which is that your law restricts the freedom of others. If some people don’t mind a game with the opposed features and your law prevents it from being made, your actions may become rather questionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps we need to think outside the box more. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://equilibriabook.com&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inadequate Equilibria&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Eliezer Yudkowsky mentions the idea of a timed-collective-action-threshold-conditional-commitment, essentially a generalized version of Kickstarter, as a means to coordinate action. In our case, the idea would be to have potential boycotters agree to the boycott if and only if a certain number of other people also agree to it. The problem is that there remains a need for an enforcement mechanism. In Kickstarter’s case, backers pay when they make the agreement and their money is returned if the project fails to meet its funding threshold. Thus, backers don’t have the option to not pay, but must instead trust the company to not keep the money for a failed project. A similar solution might work for boycotting video games, though there are multiple challenges to overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, participants need to have not already bought the game. If those who have purchased the game are allowed to appear to participate, then we will once again end up in a situation where no one is incentivized to actually participate. For the same reason, participants must be incentivized to avoid purchasing the game in the middle of the boycott. We also want to ensure that all participants are actually interested in buying the game being boycotted so the publisher is incentivized to meet the boycott’s demands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking this into account, here is my rough proposal for a Kickstarter-like boycott company. A boycott agreement would have participants deposit enough money to buy the game being boycotted. After a set time, if a set number of people has not been reached, the deposit is returned and no obligations remain. However, if the set number of people is reached prior to the set time, the boycott begins. At this point, any participant who buys the game will lose their deposit. Those who don’t buy the game will have one of two things happen to their deposit. If the boycott is judged successful, their deposit is used to purchase the game for them. However, if a set duration passes without the boycott being judged successful, the deposits are returned. Alternatively, they could be put towards purchasing a similar game by a rival publisher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why use something like this structure? The deposit is important because it serves as the enforcement mechanism. If you fail to remain in the boycott, you lose money. A successful boycott leads to the deposit buying the game for two reasons. First of all, it provides an incentive not to buy the game prior to the end of the boycott even if you could do so without being detected (such as by using an alternate account), since you’ll end up getting two copies of the game if it succeeds. It also helps discourage people who don’t care about the game from participating, which is important if they are otherwise incentivized to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason such people might be incentivized to participate is that the deposits of anyone who buys the game during the boycott might be redistributed to those who didn’t buy it. This would create an opportunity for profit that might be exploited. Other ways to prevent this include forcing deposits to be put toward another game upon a failed boycott or letting the company running the boycott keep the forfeited deposits as extra profit. The first option has the advantage of reducing the chance that participants buy the game after the boycott is over, which makes the boycott more credible to the publisher. However, it may discourage people from participating since their control over the money they deposit is vastly reduced. Letting the boycott company keep the deposits has the drawback of incentivizing the company to have some people buy the game during the boycott.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still plenty of problems with this design, and I’m sure that, if it is not entirely useless, it would at the very least need to undergo several rounds of improvement to actually be viable. But it would be very interesting if a company loosely resembling this proposal arose one day. In the meantime, there is one last idea I’d like to take a look at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of using a boycott, we could instead treat the desired action as a public good that players would like the publisher to create. Normally public goods are provided by the government, but we’ve already considered a way the government could help, so let’s look at a more unique option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Prediction_market&quot;&gt;Prediction markets&lt;/a&gt; are a special type of stock market involving assets that pay out only if a certain event happens. They are usually discussed in the context of their ability to aggregate information about currently unresolved facts. However, Paul Sztorc has &lt;a href=&quot;http://bitcoinhivemind.com/papers/3_PM_Applications.pdf&quot;&gt;proposed&lt;/a&gt; that a decentralized prediction market could be used to fund public goods. In our case, the “public good” is an end to whatever we wanted to boycott. To fund it, a special prediction market would be created, and players who wish to help fund the good would buy the state predicting that the good will not be created. If enough funds are raised, the company will choose to purchase a state predicting the creation of the good and discontinue the activity in order to claim the funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This strategy also has its share of problems. For one thing, a decentralized prediction market has to exist in order to implement this idea. Even if this condition is met, there’s still the issue of incentives to become a free rider instead of contributing to the funding of the public good. There’s also the question of whether it’s right for players to have to pay extra in order for publishers to listen to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a multitude of ways in which the weaknesses of boycotts could be overcome. While the ideas presented here are unrefined, I think there may be potential within them. That said, I have no plans to refine them myself, so it’s probable that nothing will ever come of them. However, I will not be surprised if someone eventually comes up with something.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>Video game boycotts</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/01/26/video-game-boycotts"/>
			<updated>2018-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/01/26/video-game-boycotts</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, many people have been upset by the direction some video games have been taking in regard to certain ideas like loot boxes. One proposed solution is to boycott the offending games. However, there is a fundamental problem with boycotting that makes this very difficult to pull off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participating in a boycott is generally not worth it to an individual. A good way to observe this is to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thoughtco.com/introduction-to-marginal-analysis-1147610&quot;&gt;marginal analysis&lt;/a&gt;. The marginal cost of participating in a boycott is pretty easy to identify, since it’s simply being unable to purchase and play the game targeted by the boycott. However, identifying the marginal benefit is a bit more complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to think of the marginal benefit is to assume that there is a single threshold at which it becomes more profitable for the game developer to give in to the boycott than to continue on with whatever activity is being boycotted. Below this threshold, the revenue lost to the boycotters is less than that gained by continuing the boycotted activity. At and above this threshold, continuing the activity will cost the firm more than it earns them. Thus, the firm will cease the activity if and only if the boycott meets the threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--break--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for boycotting’s marginal benefit? Well, there’s exactly one person who will bump the number of boycotters up to the threshold. The marginal benefit for this individual is the success of the boycott in changing the company’s behavior. However, for everyone else the marginal benefit of participating in the boycott is nothing. After all, they have no effect on whether or not the company continues the activity. Since the marginal cost is greater than the marginal benefit for at least all but one individual, including everyone who joins the boycott early on (well before the threshold is reached), no one is actually incentivized to participate unless exactly one specific large number of disincentivized people are already participating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One detail this model fails to account for is uncertainty regarding the location of the threshold. Unless the boycotters can figure out how much the company is profiting from the boycotted activity, they aren’t able to determine which person will reach the threshold. Thus, instead of giving definitive marginal benefits for each person, we can instead model individuals as having a marginal benefit based on the subjective probability that they will reach an unknown threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say that, without a boycott, a game would be purchased by 10 million people. For the sake of simplicity, we’ll assume that every additional person has an equal chance to reach the threshold. We’ll also assume that there is no chance of reaching the threshold with zero participants, and that all 10 million people participating guarantees that the threshold will be reached. This means that every person increases the probability of a successful boycott by .00001%. Since the &lt;a href=&quot;https://conceptually.org/concepts/expected-value/&quot;&gt;expected value&lt;/a&gt; of the marginal benefit is equal to the probability of the threshold being reached multiplied by the value of reaching the threshold, we find that a person must value purchasing and playing the game less than .00001% as much as they value the boycott succeeding in order to be incentivized to participate. In other words, unless they want to end the boycotted activity 10 million times as badly as they want to buy and play the game, they will not join the boycott. In fact, that number will always be equal to the number of potential players, so a game that is bought by only 1 million people still requires the players to want the boycott to succeed 1 million times as much as they want to buy and play the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it such a big deal that boycotts normally fail? Sure, it’s upsetting that the company won’t stop doing whatever the players hate, but some trade-off has to be made, and getting the game seems to be worth more to them than stopping the company. The problem becomes apparent when you consider what would happen if the players were able to perfectly coordinate as a single group. In this case, the group’s marginal cost and marginal benefit for participating in a boycott are equal to the total cost and total benefit of the boycott. The marginal cost is still being unable to purchase and play the game, but the marginal benefit is now a guaranteed successful boycott. Thus, every player in the group wants the group to boycott the game, assuming the players are willing to wait a short period prior to the boycott’s success to purchase the game in return for actually getting that success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this result different from when we consider the players acting individually? Because the additional cost for each player joining the boycott is only born by that player while the additional benefit is shared among every player, the fraction of the total benefit the player receives is too small to incentivize them to participate. However, if participating meant they received that sliver of benefit plus a sliver of benefit from every other player, and not participating meant they received no benefit at all, then their marginal benefit is increased to the point where they will participate. Without the players coordinating as a group, the second condition cannot be met thanks to players receiving the benefit from boycotters even if they do not participate themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This situation is an example of what is known as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://conceptually.org/concepts/coordination-problems/&quot;&gt;coordination problem&lt;/a&gt;. Without coordination, each player will take an action that makes them better off but leaves everyone else worse off, leading to the group as a whole being worse off as well. However, if the players are able to coordinate, than they can take an action that leaves themselves worse off but makes everyone else better off, leading to all members of the group being better off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, players are unable to coordinate effectively, leading to situations in which supposed boycotters are actually playing the game they wish for everyone to boycott. This is the optimal strategy for individuals since it allows the players to gain the benefits of continuing to play the game while also giving them some additional benefit from anyone foolish enough to actually do as they say and boycott the game. But from the perspective of the group, it’s a terrible outcome that both causes the boycott to fail and encourages deception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/MLZ0bMu.png&quot; alt=&quot;A photo showing members of a boycott group playing the game they want boycotted&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Not exactly the most effective group&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there ways to resolve this problem? Possibly, but I don’t think there are any easy solutions. Coordinating large groups is a very complex task, and I’m not sure how much insight I really have regarding this issue. Nonetheless, I will likely propose potential solutions in another post.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<title>This now exists</title>
			<link href="http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/01/23/this-now-exists"/>
			<updated>2018-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
			<id>http://bternarytau.github.io/2018/01/23/this-now-exists</id>
			<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I guess this site exists now. I wonder if it will die before anyone else sees it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
		</entry>
	

</feed>
